<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prompters packet of private and familar letters fitted (in sundrie formes) to mens seuerall occasions and according to the qualitie of persons. Not vnworthy imitation of the most: but most necessarie for such as want either facultie or facilitie to endight.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838348</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1114:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prompters packet of private and familar letters fitted (in sundrie formes) to mens seuerall occasions and according to the qualitie of persons. Not vnworthy imitation of the most: but most necessarie for such as want either facultie or facilitie to endight.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[79] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradwood for Sa. Macham, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls church-yard at the signe of the Bull-head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A forme of writing letters.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K (-K8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letter writing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:1"/>
            <p>THE PROMPTERS PACKET OF PRI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ATE AND Familiar Letters: Fitted (in ſundrie formes) to mens ſeuerall Occaſions, and according to the qualitie of Perſons. Not vnworthy Imitation of the moſt: But moſt neceſſarie for ſuch as want either facultie or faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to endight.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Melchiſedech Bradwood for Sa. Macham, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Bull-head.</p>
            <p>1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any there are, vnto whom is not giuen a ſpirit inuentiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that they are alwaies to ſeeke when the neceſsitie of their affaires cals them to write. Againe there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in whom is no ſuch defect of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, but yet are as much troubled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the manner of deliuering their minds. To direct either and both of theſe then what and how to write, was this Worke eſpecially vndertaken, in hope neuertheleſſe it would not prooue
<pb facs="tcp:2723:3"/> altogether ſo vnuſefull for ſuch abler iudgements as feele not theſe others want in themſelues, but that they may meet with ſomething in it whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may doe them ſeruice. So much concerning the generall frame of the Worke. For the Letters in particular, there is not added vnto euery one a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription or ſubſcription, but only to ſo many as might ſuffice to inſtance with ſome variety what is proper and beſt faſhionable in that kinde. And for their Contents, they are expreſſed in a Table heere following; whereunto ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing recourſe, a man may finde dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction there to any ſuch Letter as ſhall neereſt agree with the nature of the buſineſſe he hath in hand.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:3"/>
            <head>A briefe Table of the <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Arguments of theſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Letters.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>EXcuſe for ſeldome writing: with proteſtation of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection and ready ſeruice.</item>
               <item>Recommendation of a worthy perſon to the acquaintance &amp; aſſiſtance of ſome ſpecial friend.</item>
               <item>A pretty preuention of excuſe for ſeldome writing, concluding with friendly complement.</item>
               <item>To importune the interceſſion of one friend toward another, for diſpatch in a money mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or other caſe of importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</item>
               <item>A curteous offer, and kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:2723:4"/> of friendly offices.</item>
               <item>An earneſt expoſtulation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to letters long omitted.</item>
               <item>A complaint of wants, with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement ſolicitation of a friend to get in debts, by faire means (if it may be,) or by foule, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then faile.</item>
               <item>A ſhort quarrell of vnkindnes for not writing: concluding in a vow of perpetuall amity.</item>
               <item>A thankfull acknowledgement of kindneſſes receiued, and wel entertaining of a ſeruant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended.</item>
               <item>A gratefull acknowledgement of kinde offices towards ones Sonne, with requeſt to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the fame.</item>
               <item>A briefe recommendation of a friend.</item>
               <item>An acknowledgement of curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb facs="tcp:2723:4"/> vndeſerued.</item>
               <item>A mild taxation for not writing, and for ſome ſeeming negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in proſecution of a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
               <item>A witty excuſe for long intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of writing.</item>
               <item>A due acknowledgement of true friendſhip, which (eſpecially) in aduerſity is more apparant than in proſperity.</item>
               <item>A thankfull acknowledgement to one that hath well reported of vs when occaſion hath been offered.</item>
               <item>A ſad and ſerious complaint of a frends vnkindnes &amp; ingratitude.</item>
               <item>Recommendation of a poor man to the fauour and furtherance of ſome worthy friend.</item>
               <item>An earneſt proteſtation of ſincere affection: with ſome touch of
<pb facs="tcp:2723:5"/> vnkindnes taken for too light beleefe of ſiniſter reports.</item>
               <item>A pleaſant complement, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the contempt of the Court, and content of a reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red life.</item>
               <item>Recommendation of an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary man to the woorthy friendſhip of ſome honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſon.</item>
               <item>Reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of one friend to anothers fauour &amp; aſſiſtance.</item>
               <item>A promiſe of our beſt endeuor in the education of a child; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome doubts of his capacity and inclination.</item>
               <item>A ſecond reproofe, or rather the doubling of a friendly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</item>
               <item>A briefe diſcourſe concerning the progreſſion (or rather the ſucceſſion and viciſſitude of
<pb facs="tcp:2723:5"/> Learning; ſometimes flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in one Climate, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in another.</item>
               <item>An excellent and extraordinary letter of commendation.</item>
               <item>A gratefull acceptation of a friendly gift, with modeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe of things, exceeding ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the giuers meanes, or the receiuers merit.</item>
               <item>An earneſt diſſwaſiue from a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and couetous courſe of life.</item>
               <item>An expoſtulation of vnkind miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceits &amp; iealouſies in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</item>
               <item>Conſolation for the death of a Brother or other friend.</item>
               <item>A complement full of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of courteſies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</item>
               <item>A graue interceſsion to a Father for a Sonne that hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb facs="tcp:2723:6"/> with friendly teſtimony of his hopefull towardnes.</item>
               <item>A ſhort complement vpon receit of ſome new curteſie.</item>
               <item>Excuſe for too rare writing, vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with all the proſecution of ſome buſineſſe, vpon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the death of a friend, the election of another in his ſtead.</item>
               <item>Thankful acceptance of a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie counſell, aduiſing to follow (or ſerue) ſome great man: whence ariſeth an obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cold recompence of ſeruices in theſe daies in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of times paſt.</item>
               <item>Vpon ſubmiſsion of a runnagate and vntuly ſon, the kind father (vnder hand) commends him to the ſeruice of a woorthy friend, vnder whoſe ſhelter,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:6"/> neceſſity had already driuen him.</item>
               <item>Excuſe for not comming to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate a friends Returne; with proteſtation and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of affection with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt.</item>
               <item>Thankfull acknowledgement of kindneſſes vnto ones Sonne.</item>
               <item>A priuate taxation of the publike ingratitude of great perſons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuch as haue beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of them.</item>
               <item>Excuſe for not ſaluting a friend paſſing by vs: endeuouring (by the way) to wipe away his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of pride or of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</item>
               <item>A ſad commemoration of ſome worthy friend deceaſed.</item>
               <item>A gratefull acknowledgement of an eſpeciall fauour from any
<pb facs="tcp:2723:7"/> great man.</item>
               <item>A ſhort and ſweet conſolation in the death of friends.</item>
               <item>A modeſt complement extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our own deſert in any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour done our friend, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging all to be but duty.</item>
               <item>A gentle and eaſie ſubmiſsion to ſome new direction or altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our commiſsion.</item>
               <item>Recommendation of a forward ſon to the fauor and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome famous captain in the wars.</item>
               <item>A complement moſt officious &amp; affectionate to a Lady, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome ſerious affairs of hers</item>
               <item>A pleaſant Irony, in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law, and the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of Law ſutes.</item>
               <item>A pretty controuerſie compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a wittie complement.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:7"/>
               <item>A briefe anſwer to a bitter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement vpon a falſe ground.</item>
               <item>An earneſt and elegant intreaty, importuning the aſſiſtance of ſome friend in any matter of importance, and that with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition.</item>
               <item>A kind quarrel of vnkindnes with a friend for leauing vs vnſeene &amp; vnſaluted hauing in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner paſſed by our doore.</item>
               <item>Interceſſion for fauour &amp; remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the behalfe of one that hath offended, and is vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly ſorrie for his fault.</item>
               <item>To importune a friend to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute to perfection any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe already begun.</item>
               <item>A particular account of ſundrie buſineſſes committed to ones care.</item>
               <item>A moſt Chriſtian conſolation of
<pb facs="tcp:2723:8"/> a friend in any croſſe or afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>An earneſt recommendation of a well qualified ſeruant, to ſome place worthy of his parts.</item>
               <item>An amorous complement vpon the firſt ſight, or after ſome ſhort parley.</item>
               <item>An earneſt proteſtation of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue and loyaltie.</item>
               <item>A ſad extaſie for the abſence of your Miſtreſſe.</item>
               <item>A Loue-letter, or the ſum of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Rhetorike, in two figures, viz. <hi>Flatterie</hi> and <hi>Faining.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another of like Argument.</item>
               <item>Another not vnlike.</item>
               <item>Another of the ſame.</item>
               <item>Another, no leſſe earneſt, though perhaps leſſe honeſt.</item>
               <item>A friendly anſwer to ſuch a ſuter.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_superscriptions">
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:8"/>
            <head>A FORME OF Superſcription of Letters.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>TO my very honourable good Lord.</item>
                  <item>To the right honourable my eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good Lord and Maſter, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>To the noble and euery way excellent Lady, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>To my honourable friend Sir &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>To my euer honoured friend Sir &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>To my worthie friend.</item>
                  <item>To my truly worthy friend.</item>
                  <item>To my well eſteemed friend.</item>
                  <item>To my very much eſteemed friend.</item>
                  <item>To my dearely eſteemed friend.</item>
                  <item>To my worthily eſteemed friend.</item>
                  <item>To my moſt respected friend.</item>
                  <item>To my much reſpected friend.</item>
                  <item>To my worthily reſpected friend.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2723:9"/>
                  <item>To my more than ordinarily reſpected friend.</item>
                  <item>To my endeared and worthy friend.</item>
                  <item>To my deareſt friend.</item>
                  <item>To my euer kindeſt friend.</item>
                  <item>To my truly louing friend.</item>
                  <item>To my much approoued friend.</item>
                  <item>To my well approoued friend.</item>
                  <item>To my approoued deare friend.</item>
                  <item>To my reuerend friend.</item>
                  <item>To my very learned friend.</item>
                  <item>To my learned and iudicious friend.</item>
                  <item>To the right Worſhipfull my very good Maſter M. &amp;c. Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>To my highly eſteemed friend.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2723:9"/>
            <head>A FORME OF WRITING <hi>Letters.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Excuſe for ſeldome writing, with proteſtation of ſincere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and readie ſeruice.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, The continuall emploiment of my affaires will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to write oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vnto you: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:10"/> whenſoeuer you haue occaſion to vſe my ſeruice, they ſhall not ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ruls me. For my affection to you is no leſſe then your vertue, and the many offices of kindnes which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore you haue done me, do require. Neither is this affection of mine pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the outward complement of words, but in the interiour of my heart, where, though it ſeeme to lie hid and concealed, yet ſhall it be ſure to ſhew it ſelfe at al times when any point appertaining either to your profit or honour ſhall come in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this your experience ſhall vndoubtedly make good vpon euerie occaſion wherein I may be ſo much fauoured of fortune as to be made apt for your vſe. In the meane time I remaine,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Wholly at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:10"/>
               <head>Recommendation of a woorthy perſon, to the acquaintance and aſſiſtance of ſome ſpeciall friend.</head>
               <p>SIr: My purpoſe is not by any long or artificiall letter, to violate the lawes of our ancient and perfect friendſhip, nor offer wrong to your curteſie and ſingular iudgement in the commendation of this friend <hi>M. P.</hi> who being a Gentleman of ſorte, and of ſuch parts, that all that know him are induced not only to loue, but to honour him, it ſhall ſuffice mee to ſay he is my friend, and worthy to be yours, the reſt you will finde in him your ſelfe, beeing well aſſured that hauing once knowne him, his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance will bee very déere vnto you. He comes to towne about cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his affaires, wherein he ſhall haue néede of your counſell and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor: and I cannot doubt, that either you will neglect the goodnes of your owne diſpoſition, or his merit, not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2723:11"/> much for that I entreat it, as becauſe your vertue perſwades it, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it. I ſhall be very glad to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that hee may finde you a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall diſpenſer of theſe offices, and you him a thankfull and woorthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer of them. And I thinke not but you will as much acknowledge vnto me the notice I haue giuen you of ſuch a gentleman, together with the meanes to do him pleaſure, as he the entrance I haue made him into the poſſeſſion of your friendſhip. Loue one another then (as I know you will) and in your loue reſerue mée ſuch place as I hope I deſerue, and doe very much deſire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A prettie preuention of excuſe for ſeldome writing: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding with friendly complement.</head>
               <p>COſen, it imports not ſo much (as ſome ſay) that friends which
<pb facs="tcp:2723:11"/> haue alwaies made exchange of euery good office of loue, ſhould be tyed to a continuall entercourſe of letters. For report that takes account of al things carries from one to another newes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of both. And for proofe of it, I am perſwaded that ere it be long, you will vnderſtand by it of all that I doe, as by the ſame meane I am oftentimes acquainted with your courſes: ſo that it is as good as a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to vs with letters, wherein we may take no leſſe pleaſure, then the eye doth in picture: foraſmuch as ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mor is nothing elſe but an open letter where euery man may reade what him liſt. Wherefore neuer go about to excuſe your ſelfe vnto mee of that, whereof for my part I neuer meane to excuſe my ſelfe vnto you: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue me in your memorie with this opinion, that you haue as much pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ouer mée and my beſt meanes, as ouer any of your owne: neither is it with bare offers, or the common ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of a good will, that I deſire
<pb facs="tcp:2723:12"/> you ſhould be ſatiſfied: for I am of the religion that makes a nullitie of faith without workes, and therefore bee aſſured to finde mee much better then my word in all your occaſions: to the experience whereof I referre you, and my ſelfe to be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alwaies at your ſeruice.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To importune the Interceſſion of one friend toward another, for diſpatch in a money matter, or other caſe of importance.</head>
               <p>SIr, I may iuſtly vaunt, that I carrie a minde more apt to giue then to take. But God be thanked and my fortune, I haue often times cauſe to aſke, but very ſeldome pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe a pleaſure. And I reioice more when I haue meanes to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my friend, then I grieue when I am to importune them. It may bée
<pb facs="tcp:2723:12"/> now you may thinke this is ſome preamble of neceſſitie. I am conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you ſhould take it ſo. <hi>M. Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> though my penſion hath béene due a month and more, ſaith he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pay me without an expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from my Lo. and that alſo he hath no mony. Now I that haue more occaſions vpon my backe then crownes in my purſe, doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from this excuſe, and making you the Iudge of it, doe earneſtly pray, nay coniure you, by that cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie which yet hath neuer failed mée in my néed, not to ſuffer ſentence to paſſe againſt me: but as a fauour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together deriued from the goodneſſe of your diſpoſition, let my occaſions through your interpoſure, finde ſuch ſupply as their preſent extremity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. And at any hand, I beſéech you, ſo deale, that the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> may not ſay he hath no money: for that would prooue a feauer to him, and a plague to me: againſt the which hoping to receiue a preſeruatiue in
<pb facs="tcp:2723:13"/> your returne héereunto I leaue you to the compoſing of it, and my ſelfe</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Very deſirous in euery thing to ſerue you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A curteous offer, and kind accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of friendly Offices.</head>
               <p>WIth more Honour, and by a more worthy perſon, you might haue preſented your letters vnto my Lord: but not by any that with more affection and deſire would vndertake the office then my ſelfe. And that not onely for your ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (the which yet I eſpecially regard) but alſo for mine owne content, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatly to my reputation that a Gentleman of ſuch worth and eſtéem as your ſelfe, ſhould make choice of me for ſo good an employment. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much thanke <hi>M. C.</hi> for giuing your memory that addreſſe, and mée
<pb facs="tcp:2723:13"/> the meanes to doe you ſeruice, if that may be caled ſeruice which redounds to my credit. Thurſdaie next my Lord will be vpon returne, and then with the beſt commodity I will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what it hath pleaſed you to command, and of all accordingly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe you. In euerie other occaſion for your ſeruice, I humbly beſeech you not to ſpare mee, to the end that by the way of your commandement, I may get out of theſe bonds wherin I ſtand ſo obliged vnto you, as well for diuers other fauours, as eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for this you preſentlie doe me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An earneſt expoſtulation of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to letters long omitted.</head>
               <p>SIr, I wrote twice vnto you by a young man of this place, and it is ſo long agoe that I am almoſt out of hope of anſwer: neuertheleſſe if he be not dead by the way, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, or that you bee in health, as I
<pb facs="tcp:2723:14"/> much deſire, and ſtil retaine the ſame opinion of mee my friendſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, let me entreat you to rid me of this feare, which is much increaſed by the comming of this meſſenger, without letters from you. For though I were not at home, you might not thinke me ſo far, or ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, but that your letters would haue found mee out. I wrote vnto you then at large of the greatnes of my buſineſſe, and what reſolution I had taken, I will not trouble you therefore with any repetition, but onely now deſire you to conſider that new friendſhip is not to be preferred to the ſurety of olde, which like olde wines are euery way better than new. For mine owne part, I loue you in the fame degrée with my ſelfe, and in ſuch manner, that I deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then to be acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I hope you are ſo enclined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me: otherwiſe I ſhould doubt that not finding me of ability to giue you any promiſe of profit, your frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:2723:14"/> is therefore decayed: which would proue an incongruity of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and offence of iudgement. But not fearing that euer you will fall into any ſuch error, I commit you to a returne, and my ſelfe to an expectation of your anſwere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A complement of Wants with vehement ſolicitation of a friend to get in debts by faire means (if it may bee) or by foule rather then faile.</head>
               <p>GOOD Nephew, I know I ſhould very much wrong your loue in recommending my affaires vnto you, but neceſſity which cannot brooke delay, compels me vnto it. I am altogether without money, and many things are wanting in my houſe: now iudge whether I haue not reaſon to preſſe you: with ſome
<pb facs="tcp:2723:15"/> importunity for the getting in of ſuch as are there owing mee. Thoſe good debtors of mine, eſpecially the party you wot of, are like dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ades, that will not ſtir a foot without ſpurring. Wherefore, ſeeing that both my oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and the ſlacknes of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture require it, I pray you egge them forward, and if the ſpurre will not ſerue, lay them on and ſpare not, you muſt remember that the end of this moneth will be the end of your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and my hopes. For if you with all the loue you beare me, together with the meanes &amp; deſire you haue to doe me pleaſure, cannot bring theſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to any good paſſe, what ſhould I expect from thoſe whom héereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I muſt employ that ſhall haue lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ability and happily leſſe will. The gentleman you mentioned in your laſt, I haue not yet ſéene, neither doe I thinke his ſight wil bring me more commoditity then pleaſure, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hee is a fellow that promiſeth mountaines, but neuer performs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:2723:15"/> thing: and introth I know not what to ſay to him, for I finde ſuch a diſtanes betwéene his words and works, that now I begin to hope ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to hope on him more. I wil trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you no farther but onely to put <hi>M. G.</hi> in minde of my ſuite, to the end his promiſes may bring foorth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects like themſelues; and ſo very timelie I commit you to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A ſhort quarrell of vnkindnes for not writing: concluded in a vow of perpetuall Amitie.</head>
               <p>SIr, it a long poſſeſſion with you were turnd into cuſtom, I ſhould accuſe you: for ſuffering one of your folkes to come hither with empty hands. But the trueth is, though I am ſorry for that I haue receiued no letters from you, yet am I not ſo ſorry for that default, as in that it is
<pb facs="tcp:2723:16"/> a certaine ſigne vnto mee that as yet you haue not thought vpon your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne becauſe wee neuer receiue let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from you, but when you are vpon the point of your comming hither. Howſoeuer, be aſſured that neither your letters nor the want of them ſhall giue any encreaſe or diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that teſpect and loue I beare you, hauing alwaies made this a firme determination with my ſelfe, to be ſtill the ſame I euer haue béene and am vnto you, I meane your</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Humble ſeruant and friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A thankfull acknowledgement of kindneſſes receiued: and well entertaining of a ſeruant recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</head>
               <p>GOOD Coſen, not being able in better manner to anſwer the
<pb facs="tcp:2723:16"/> greatnes of the obligation, wherin I ſtand engaged vnto you for the good remembrance it pleaſeth you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to haue of me, I muſt entreat you to reſt contented with an infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thankes I preſently ſend you, vntill ſuch time as occaſion ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh mée with meanes to make you a more worthy ſatisfaction. I am very ſorry my fortunes are worſe then competent, and that for diuerſe reaſons, among the which I account it not the leaſt that I cannot make prouiſion correſpondent to the merit of the young man you recommended vnto me. I know not what his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement hath béene otherwhere, neuertheleſſe if he be as you ſay, I will ſtraine my ſelfe in cutting off ſome leſſe conſiderable charge to giue him his demand. But before we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede any farther, I would willingly haue him ſend mee an eſſay of his hand, to the end that he being ſure of his wages, and I of the qualitie of his ſeruice, both of vs may remaine
<pb facs="tcp:2723:17"/> ſatisfied, for touching the reſt I wholy referre me to your iudgment: ſo with all affection I commend mée vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A gratefull acknowledgement of kind Offices towards ones Sonne, with requeſt to continue the ſame.</head>
               <p>SIr, I am to giue you many thanks for the fauours it hath pleaſed you to ſhew my ſonne. This is not the firſt kindeneſſe I haue recetued from you and yours, neither was my gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant worthy of it, conſidering his fault. But you haue béene vnto him as a <hi>Pſacos</hi> in the middeſt of a darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſaue him from the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, which without you, he had aſſuredly ſuffered. I know not what will be the iſſue of it, pray God your prognoſtication may proue true. I
<pb facs="tcp:2723:17"/> haue entreated. <hi>M. P.</hi> to ioine with you, and ſupply my want of preſence in exhortations. I haue alſo deſired. <hi>M. F.</hi> to take him into his houſe, and I hope he will not denie mée. The form of his voyage hath much diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me: it may be God will turn it all to the beſt. But to tell you, what I think, nothing ſurely can be truer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith to his wife. <hi>That the pleaſure which wee take in our children is full of anguiſh:</hi> neither is it without cauſe that <hi>Saint Ierome</hi> hath diſcourſed very much in one of his epiſtles, without any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reſolution taken thereupon, whether of the two were moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, either to marry or not to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For my part I beléeue this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion may be concluded by that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Martiall.</hi> For doubtleſſe hée that hath no children takes not ſo much pleaſure as he that hath: but withall hee endures not that trouble and vexation of mind the other doth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:18"/>
               <head>A briefe recommendation of a Friend.</head>
               <p>SIr, I ſhould rather merit reproch then reputation, to recommend vnto you the affaires of <hi>M. G.</hi> the preſent bearer. For to his knowledge your bounty is ſuch, that it exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth euen to thoſe you neuer ſawe. I leaue you then to imagin what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hee may haue of it that hath known you ſo long, and that by his own vertues ſufficiently commends himſelfe, and that is alſo commended vnto you by one of your moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate frends. Touching the requeſt he ſhall offer for my cauſe, I will not preſſe you much in it, beeing aſſured you wil not do your ſelfe that wrong to deny me: for conſidering that by our ancient friendſhip we two are but as one, the refuſall you ſhould make me would but ſhew the little regard you carry vnto your ſelfe. And ſo very kindly for this time I take my leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:18"/>
               <head>An acknowledgement of curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies vndeſerued.</head>
               <p>I Receiue no letter from <hi>M. I.</hi> that is not accompanied with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſingular mention of the many good Offices you continually doe for me, which altogether procéeds from the goodnes of your owne diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition without any merit at all of mine, and I were worthy to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the number of the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull that euer were, if at the leaſt I did not acknowledge it by letters, vntill ſuch time as I may méet with ſome happy occaſion to deſerue it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: wherein I writ to employ my ſelfe with ſo good a will and affection that you ſhall neuer repent any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you haue done vnto him, that deſires nothing more then to appeare how much he is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Truely your friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:19"/>
               <head>A mild taxation for not writing, and for ſome ſeeming negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in proſecuting of a buſineſſe.</head>
               <p>SIr, your ſlacknes rather deſerueth blame then excuſe in my behalfe, and I am glad you are fallen into the ſame error whereof you haue ſo often accuſed me. Your letters at all times would be very welcome, but much more now being ſo deſirous to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what ſucceſſe hath followed my kinſmans buſineſſe, which not long ſince with ſuch care I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto you. I cannot doubt that you haue forgotten him, the matter concerning him ſo much, and hee a man ſo vnworthy and vnfit to ſuffer a neglect: beſides I haue many times heard you ſay that an iniury in that kind is a cauſe iuſt and ſufficient enough to diſſolue all friendſhip. But to come againe to my firſt quarrell, I know if you ſhould be called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb facs="tcp:2723:19"/> before the God of reſpect, for all your eloquence you would be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeither for a negligent or an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate friend. Neuertheleſſe ſéeing you haue had no good opportunity to write, I pardon this ſilence, and as one that holds you deare, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe with your beſt leiſure, and conueniencie. I make no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but that you and the reſt of our friends there looke for ſome great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence at my hands, but I am not able to ſatiſfie you with the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of note. For matters of the ſtate lye ſo déep buried in the graue of ſecrecy, that no man can come to haue a ſight of them but with the eye of reaſon, which iudgeth wel enough of that which ſhould bee, but not of that which ſhall be. Wherefore you muſt be therewith contented vntill the reſt ſhall come to light. And ſo I pray you continue me in your fauor, whereunto with all affection I very humbly commend my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:20"/>
               <head>A witty excuſe for long intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of writing.</head>
               <p>SIr, I could fetch ſome color of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for this long intermiſſion of writing, from the many affaires wherein I am continually conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant: but it would be neither worthy your acceptance, nor my affection. For there is no employment either of body or minde, that ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt any office appertaining to your pleaſure, or the ſatiſfaction of my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Wherefore leauing this excuſe which would bee more honeſt then iuſt, I will ſéeke to cléere my ſelfe with the plaine truth, and fréely tell you that I haue not written all this while becauſe I had nothing to write and that I thought letters were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſary for my occaſion, nor your contentment. If I had ſéen that to ſubſtantiate our auncient friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there had héene neede of ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiall complements. I ſhould haue
<pb facs="tcp:2723:20"/> thought it had beene grounded on a leſſe firme and weaker foundation then it is That vertuous and honeſt diſpoſition which euen from our youth and firſt acquaintance I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies found in you, hath knit our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſo faſt together, that not the ſtrength of any enemy, enuie, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worldly accidents whatſoeuer ſhall euer bée able to vndoe it. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould much wrong your iudgement, in beléeuing that you can be ſo carried away with the vulgar, as to thinke that frequency of letters is preciſely required for the fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a friendſhip. I ſhall neuer be perſwaded that any ſuch hereſie can take hold on you, or that you more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme of verball ceremony, then of action and the true entent of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt will. For my part, I haue ſtill béene more a friend of deeds, then of words, which moſt commonly little pleaſure and leſſe profit, whereas the other beget them both. My ſlacknes in writing ſhall be recompenced with
<pb facs="tcp:2723:21"/> a deſire and endeuour to doe you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in euery occaſion whereunto my poore but ableſt meanes may extend: whereof becauſe I perſwaded my ſelfe you make no doubt, I will héere with my humble and kindeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations giue end to the preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A due acknowledgement of true friendſhip, which (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) in aduerſity is more apparent then in proſperity.</head>
               <p>SIr, by your letters I perceiue you haue the ſame opinion of my loue, I alwaies deſired. I am glad I haue not bene deceiued in the iudgement of your wiſdome and good will. And ſince that true and perfect friendſhip conſiſts not in words or fair promiſes but in effects &amp; vertuous executions: I muſt needs confeſſe that I haue found you of little ſpeech and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous
<pb facs="tcp:2723:21"/> apparance in my behalfe ſo long as fortune fauoured me; but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as my troubles and occaſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan but to knocke at the gate of your aſſiſtance, you haue euer well expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the goodnes of your generous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: and I may truly ſay I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer met with any, or very few ſuch like. Wherfore be aſſured, that I wil ſerue, reſpect, and loue you, as long as I haue breath to doe it, and that too as farre from ingratitude as may bée. I know many that bragge and talke of fauours which they neuer did mée: whereas you haue dealt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally with mée, and neuer ſpoke of it. They are indebted to mee then for that which they charge mée with, but I neuer receiued: and I vnto you for many pleaſures done mee, which yet you neuer put to account. I will adde nothing héereunto, but that if I could ſend you my heart in ſtead of this paper, you ſhould ſée the integritie of my meaning. I haue ſpoken with the party you wot of,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:22"/> and my reaſons, together with your authoritie, haue ſo preuailed, that your deſire ſhall be accompliſhed. If in any other thing I may ſerue you, giue as much boldneſſe to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as you haue alwaies found in my intreaties: ſo ſhall I be confirmed in that perſwaſion I haue that you eſteeme of me as indéede I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A thankfull acknowledgement to one that hath well reported of vs when occaſion hath beene offered.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my worthy friend M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, I ſhould be too too ingratefull if I ſhould not giue you a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thankes for the honeſt mention
<pb facs="tcp:2723:22"/> you were pleaſed to make of mee in the company you wot of. Only take héede that to a purpoſe you giue not caution for him that may chance to faile you. It is not the firſt fauour you haue done mee, nor the laſt I hope to receiue from you. If there be that in me you ſpeake of, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it is for to doe you very humble ſeruice: wherein I will employ my ſelfe vpon all occaſions with as good a will as now I pray vnto God to giue you your deſires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A ſad and ſerious complaint of a friends vnkindneſſe and ingratitude.</head>
               <p>GOod friend, it is no matter of difficultie for thoſe that are in health to giue much counſell and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny receits to the ſicke. If my diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition could haue receiued comfort from the diſcréet and honeſt letters of a friend, I had found it in yours,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:23"/> which are furniſhed with all ſort of kindneſſe and accompliſhed courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. But like vnto him that thinkes he is mounted on <hi>Sedanus</hi> horſe, my obſtinate deſpaire ſets ſo ſure a watch on my thoughts, that it will ſuffer nothing to enter into them but vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and miſerie. I am ſorry your medecine cannot worke that in mee which your vertue deſerues, able in troth to draw any other out of the griefe of calamitie. But leaue mée I pray yée as I am. For there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can content mee ſo long as I know that my diſſembling friend hath violated al the lawes of honeſty and reaſon, and vtterly aboliſhed out of his memorie that loue and reſpect I euer bare him. It grieues mee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedingly that my minde is not as well able to reſiſt the aſſaults of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, as his was to execute on me all kinde of ingratitude: to the end that in this affaire I might as eaſily haue borne his wrongs, as héereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue faithfully acquited my
<pb facs="tcp:2723:23"/> ſelfe in ſo many commandements hée hath laid vpon me. Deare friend, if your loue extend ſo farre as I cannot doubt but it doth, ſuffer mée to be as I am a moſt infortunate man, and reſt you with your faire and kinde bedfellow in all happineſſe, which I will alwaies pray may be more and more increaſed, and continued long vpon you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Recommendation of a poore man to the fauour and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie friend.</head>
               <p>SIr, I know I cannot pleaſe you better, then to preſent you with meanes to imploy thoſe abilities of your good and liberall diſpoſition on ſome ſuch perſon as ſhall haue occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to vſe them. A qualitie no doubt aboue all others worthy, honeſt, and acceptable to God. Wherefore I
<pb facs="tcp:2723:24"/> that of this affection both in others and mine own particular, haue made ſuch good experience, doe eſpecially labour, being ſo faithfull a ſeruant and friend vnto you as I am, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie you therein; hoping withall by this meane to bee able to cléere ſome part of thoſe many obligations wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſtand ſo farre ingaged vnto you. The bearer héereof is a poore man that is going to <hi>London</hi> about cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine affaires, whereof you ſhall bee aduertiſed by him at large: hee ſhall haue very much néede of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and countenance. A beſéech you Sir, impart vnto him of thoſe your fauours, wherein you are ſo rich and abundant, that you cannot depart with ſo many as there will bée many more remaining behinde. And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of merit, you are to hope for more in the behalfe of this man, then of any other that euer you ſuccoured, by reaſon his pouertie and want of meanes wil neuer ſuffer him ſo much as to thinke of requitall. Héerein fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="tcp:2723:24"/> but your owne worthy inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and reioice with your ſelfe at the excellencie of knowledge that is ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in you to this, that you haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther péere nor ſuperiour in courteſie. Whereunto I very humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſelfe, and you to that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from whom I will daily wiſh you all proſperitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An earneſt proteſtation of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere affection: with ſome touch of vnkindneſſe taken for too light beleefe of ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reports.</head>
               <p>GOod Sir, I would my heart lay as open to the view of your eie, as the colour of a roſe doth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the cléereſt cryſtall. For then behalding in it how much I trulie loue and reſpect you, and how much beyond all others I deſire your profit and honour; I know you could not
<pb facs="tcp:2723:25"/> but thinke it a ſhame to fall into any the leaſt ſuſpition or doubt of my friendſhip. If you would haue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured your thoughts by mine, you ſhould haue ſéene that I loue you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you loue me, and that I reſpect you becauſe I am indebted to your vertue. I cannot chuſe but thinke it ſtrange that a man of ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wiſedome, and great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in all things, ſhould ſo eaſilie ſlide into error. You ſhould rather haue giuen credit to ſo many proofes you haue made of my faith and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then to the malice and enuie of men. And to ſpeake ſomewhat fréely vnto you: if you be perſwaded that that is true, which you tell mee you haue heard, you doe your ſelfe much wrong; for it would argue great weakneſſe in you, to giue eare to any ſuch thing: it being as vicious to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue euerie thing, as to beléeue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: for to be ouer-eaſie of beléefe, and not to beléeue at all, are couſins in vice by ſecret philoſophie. Well,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:25"/> howſoeuer it be, I will alwaies loue you as much as you ſhall deſire to bée loued of me, and as long as your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues haue any being, whereupon I haue grounded that worthy affection I beare you. Wherefore I pray you eſteeme of me not only as of a friend, but as of an eſpeciall and ſingular friend, for ſo I deſire to appeare, and ſo you ſhall be ſure to finde me aſſoone as any fit occaſion ſhall offer mée the meanes to make it good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A pleaſant complement, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the contempt of the Court, and content of a retired life.</head>
               <p>YOur man paſſing this way, came to enquire of my health, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to acquaint you at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: which in that regard hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes will be the more acceptable, by reaſon of the loue it pleaſeth you
<pb facs="tcp:2723:26"/> to beare me. Wherefore you ſhall vnderſtand that God bee thanked I am very well, and not onely I, to whom it is naturall to be well in all places, but euen a very rogue would thinke himſelfe halfe an Emperour, liuing as I doe, ſo quieilie, and ſo well retired from the ſlauerie wherin I continued but too long. I neuer was in Paradiſe (as farre as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) ſo that I cannot iuſtly ſay what the life of the bleſſed is; but ſure I am, to ſtarue héere for hunger is an happineſſe to the ſeruice of a Court: and mee thinkes a Peaſant with vs is in farre better ſtate then a great man there. When I lie in my bed, and conſider a poore ſeruant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead for cold, and fainting with heat, and ſée gréene wood to warme him, and dead drinke to refreſh him, and if he hap to be ſicke, little meanes to accommodate him; I ſée him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in raine, haile and ſnow, and when he comes in nothing to comfort him; Lord (thinke I) what a bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:2723:26"/> caſe am I in, that am as frée from theſe inconueniences, as hee is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſubiect to them. As there is no miſerie to that of a poore Courtier that is wearie and cannot ſit, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie and cannot eate, a-thirſt, and cannot drinke, and ſléepie, and yet muſt watch; ſo I am perſwaded there is no happineſſe to mine, that eat when I haue an appetite, reſt when I am wearie, and goe to bed when I am ſléepie: ſo that the houres that I tell of the clocke, are but ſo many houres of my pleaſure. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neuer enquire more how I doe, for bee aſſured I lacke nothing to make vp a full and abſolute content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but your companie, which I hope (at leaſtwiſe if you be a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of your word) I ſhall not bee long without. In the expectation whereof I will leaue my ſelfe, and you to the tuition of the Almightie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:27"/>
               <head>Recommendation of an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie man to the worthie friendſhip of ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable perſon.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my euer honoured friend Sir I. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HOnorable Sir, I acknowledge much vnto fortune for offering me occaſion at one time to ſatiſfie both Sir <hi>Thomas M.</hi> and your ſelfe ſome part of thoſe many obligations wherein I confeſſe my ſelfe to haue béene a long time indebted vnto you, and by the way of continuing friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt you, alike in goodneſſe of nature, excellencie of ſpirit, and all other qualities worthie your noble diſpoſitions: ſo that hee which might behold the face of your hearts, could hardly diſcerne the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By experiences and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:2723:27"/> opinion of the world, hée is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie poſſeſt of your vertues. And if you haue not yet heard the publike voice of renowne that goes about proclaiming his worth, may you bée pleaſed to giue credit vnto my pen, which may iuſtly ſay, that a more valiant, wiſe, vertuous, or noble gentleman, liues not this day vpon the earth. Embrace one another then at my intreatie, and with the bands of courteous offices ſo ſtraitly tie your affections together, that like the <hi>Gordian</hi> knot, no worldly acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent may be of power to diſſolue it. I aſſure my ſelfe you wil doe it with a maruellous ſatiſfaction of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But yet I beſéech you, let it not be done in ſuch manner, but that like an humble and faithfull ſeruant as I am vnto you both, I may find a place in the middeſt of your vertuous friendſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:28"/>
               <head>Recommendation of one friend to anothers fauour and aſsiſtance.</head>
               <p>SIr, if you will haue me leſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and troubleſome vnto you, I would wiſh you to become leſſe courteous towards mée. For out of your fauour I picke many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to giue you trouble. Beſides I know not how to refuſe my friends, vnleſſe I ſhould ſhew my ſelfe neglectful of them, which would prooue a very great wrong to my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>M. P.</hi> for his worthy qualities capable of your loue, is going to the Court about ſome affaires, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch whereof hee ſhall haue much néed of counſell and fauour. And not knowing any one more liberall of them then your ſelfe, hee hath verie earneſtly intreated mee to write ſomewhat more then ordinarie vnto you in his commendation. Now I that am naturally inclined to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:2723:28"/> euerie man, eſpecially thoſe vn to whom nothing ought to bee deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, haue willingly vndertaken this charge, as well to gratifie him, as to doe you ſeruice in furniſhing you with meanes to winne the heart of a gentleman of that value he is of. I cannot doubt but that you will exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your accuſtomed goodneſſe vpon him, either in regard of my intreatie, or his vertue, which is ſuch, that as ſoone as it ſhall be knowen vnto you, there will be no more néed of my let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Wherefore I will not goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by any further Art to wrong your iudgement, being well aſſured you will find that your credit ſhall be emploied, and my requeſt ſatiſfied for a very ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:29"/>
               <head>A promiſe of our beſt indeuour in the education of a Childe; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome doubts of his capacity and inclination.</head>
               <p>SIr, the loue that I beare you, procéeding from your merit and my obligation, might aſſure you: that whatſoeuer I can doe for your ſonne ſhall bee performed with all affection and good will. For the force of your entreaties cannot bee of more power in that regard then my deſire: onely it grieues me that the field of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is not ſo proper to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, as I am ready to ſow in it the ſeede of my little experience, to the end that with his profit, and my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you might ſée the fruit of my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors. He ſeemes to mée to bee borne more apt for any other exerciſe, than that ciuility, neuertheleſſe more to ſatiſfie your fancy then my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:29"/> I will alwaies keepe him neere about me: and be aſſured that if the trauell or diligence of the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can mend and better a barren ground, I will not be defectiue in his behalfe. For you ſhall vnderſtand that of all my trauell and paines, there is no fruit more deare or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to me, than that which proceeds from the graine I haue ſowen. The pleaſure which the labourer fooles, when with his owne hand he plucks the fruit hanging on the trée which he himſelfe hath planted, is very great. How much greater then ought the contentment of that man to be, who hauing endued a tender youth with good manners, gathers the fruit of vextue, comming of it. For my part I will do all that ſhall be poſſible and neceſſary, ſo that if things fall not out anſwerable to your expectation and my deſire, you may impute the fault rather to the matter, than the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:30"/>
               <head>A ſecond reproofe or rather the doubling of a friendly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition.</head>
               <p>SIr, in the letter which not long ſince you receiued from mee, and which as I am giuen to vnderſtand you receiued in euill part, I came rather drawne by a deſire of your good, and the loue that I beare you, then perſwaded by mine owne will to execute the office of reprehenſion vpon you: and as the good Phiſition that not to hurt but to heale his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent comes much againſt his mind to the vyolent remedies of fire or knife, ſo did I carry my ſelfe towards you, that if my correction could haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued pleaſing and profitable vnto you, I ſhould haue bene glad that by my means you had recouered your helth, or that therein fayling, I might at leaſtwiſe haue ſatiſfied mine owne conſcience and the duty of our frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. As from a friend then that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2723:30"/> affects you, and not as from a malicious enemy receiue the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I made you. For otherwiſe you ſhew that a flatterer is more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto you, then a friend. And I that aboue all others abhor that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and that had rather be an open e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, then a hollow friend will ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner leaue to loue you, then diſſemble with you, and rather offend you with a plaine trueth, then pleaſe you with a deceitfull lye. But pardon mee I pray you, for ſpeaking thus fréely, and conſider that your diſeaſe ſtood in need of a ſharpe, and ſtrong purge, which I wiſh may work that effect in you the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:31"/>
               <head>A briefe diſcourſe concerning the progreſſion (or rather the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion) and viciſſitude of Lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning; ſometimes flouriſhing in one Climate, ſometimes in another.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my learned friend.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, whereas you deſire a frée deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of my mind vpon the matter propounded in your laſt, I muſt néeds tell you I am not any way of your opinion to thinke that the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the Clymate can make men either more or leſſe learned, as if there were certaine countries more affected to good letters then others. I wil not deny, but that euery nation hath certaine vertues and vices, which are tranſmitted from one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as it were by an hereditarie and ſucceſſiue right: nor haue I ſéene
<pb facs="tcp:2723:31"/> any Countrey anciently taxed for a vice, which is not ſtill continuing in the poſterity, although it haue béene repeopled with new Colonies. But touching ſo much as appertaines to Sciences the diſcourſe is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as may be gathered by very o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular examples: was there euer grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perſonages in all kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; learning than in <hi>Greece,</hi> and was there euer ſo much barbariſm in the world, as that which is preſently in it: Look but vpon <hi>Affricke,</hi> in what opinion of doctrine had it euer béene in? Neuertheleſſe a little after the aduancement and progreſſe of our Chriſtian Religion, there was no country, on the earth that produced greater Doctors of the Church than it, witneſſe <hi>Tertullian, Optatius, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius, Saint Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Saint Auguſtine.</hi> After the ſame manner in the time of the Romane common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth, no nation was euer more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from good letters than <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> which both at this inſtant, and
<pb facs="tcp:2723:32"/> for ſixe or ſeuen ſcore yéers paſt hath béene ſéene to flouriſh in all kinde of ſtudies. And I may ſay for it is true that as Monarch yes, ſo learning and ſciences change their habitation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuerſity of ſeaſons. Which is the reaſon why at firſt they flouriſhed among the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> then in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> from thence they took their courſe into <hi>Greece,</hi> and laſtly vnto <hi>Rome.</hi> Afterwards we hauing béene poſſeſſed for many hundreth yeares, together with a continuall barbariſme they came at length to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne part in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and part in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> whereas yet they make their abode. And all this by a certaine reuolution of things, which is the cauſe that in ſome ages we ſée armes to proſper in a countrey, and then againe letters. Thus hauing briefly ſhewed you that euery Nation is capable of Arts and Sciences, according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of occurrences, I will leaue you to a conſideraion of my reaſons,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:32"/> and my ſelfe very ready to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by you, vpon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An excellent and extraordinary letter of Commendation.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my approued deare friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, in that I know you to bée an enemy of complement, I will write as plainely as may be, to the end my meaning may the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto you, which peraduenture couered with the vaile of Arte would be the harder for you to conceiue. This Gentleman, <hi>M. V.</hi> is a friend of mine, and deſiring to be receiued into the number of your ſeruants, he hath entreated mee to become the meanes of it. Wherupon comparing his merit with your iudgement, and
<pb facs="tcp:2723:33"/> perſwading my ſelfe that with one office I may ſatiſfie two debts, one of duty to you, the other of affection to him. I am very well coutented to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it. Now becauſe I know that in the election of friends, you &amp; I are as it were of one taſte, I aſſure my ſelfe you will iudge him worthy your friendſhip and my commendation. I will not ſpeake of what you are to do for him: for you ſhall no ſooner know him, but you will thinke you ſhould do more for him than he will require. Howſoeuer, vntill he haue obtained that which he deſireth, I meane ſo to oppreſſe you with intreaties, that my importunitie ſhall beget his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: and I hope you will not take it in euill part, foraſmuch as you know, that a man is only to intreat for himſelfe, but for his friend hée is both to intreat and importune. When for mine owne particular I ſhall haue occaſion of that fauour, which ſo many times héeretofore hath obliged me vnto you, it ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:2723:33"/> then that I will vſe that madeſtie, which the loue I iuſtly beare ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a friend as <hi>M. V.</hi> doth make mee now to forget: although I will neuer forget to commend you and all your affaires vnto him in whoſe hand is all proſperity to giue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A gratefull acceptation of a friendly gift, with modeſt refuſall of things, exceeding either the giuers meanes, or the receiuers merit.</head>
               <p>SIr, I haue receiued your letters aſwell furniſhed with good aduiſe and counſell, as with good will and affection, and I am not a little glad we both iumpe ſo well together in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that you are perſwaded that that which is for your profit and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, will be alſo for my commoditie and good. If by many other waies I
<pb facs="tcp:2723:34"/> had not made experience of your friendſhip this would bee an approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued argument vnto me of it. Now I ſhall goe with a far better will ſéeing my ſelfe carried by your direction. I humbly thanke you, for the preſent it hath pleaſed you to ſend me, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy indeed the greatnes of your mind but not my deſert: for there is no particular gaine ſhall make mee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble that which I am bound to tell you, and that is, how you are to take care not to extend your liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beyond the limit of your meanes, and that in ſéeking to ſupply your friends, you do not wrong your ſelfe. Weigh but your fortunes with my merit, and you will find that ſo great a gift doth neither belong to your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility nor my condition. I would not haue you ſo bountifull vnto mee, as that therby you ſhould want means, to be ſo vnto others of more vertue &amp; worth, for ſo I ſhould ſhew my ſelfe more a friend of mine owne profit, then your reputation. What could
<pb facs="tcp:2723:34"/> you offer to one that indeed were worthy, if you thinke this but a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle for me, that am of ſo little valew. Wee ſhould ſo giue as wee may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies haue wherewithall to giue, and ſo well manage the gates of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, that they may neither be open nor ſhut to any. With all thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe I accept of your gelding, which comes verie fit for the iourney I haue in hand: but the mony I haue returned back again to the fountaine of your bounty, that there may not lacke water for thoſe that deſerue it better then I, and that (it may be) are more athirſt. If you come not hither before my departure, I will be with you aſſoone as conuenientlie I may, to acknowledge ſome part of thoſe manie fauours I continually receiue at your hands. In the meane time I wiſh your fortunes anſwerable to your free and generous diſpoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:35"/>
               <head>An earneſt diſſwaſiue from a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and couetous courſe of life.</head>
               <p>SIr, the affection that I beare you is the onelie cauſe to make mee ſo deſirous of your good as preſently I am. Reputation (me thinks) is one of the principall and chiefeſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes we enioy in this world and as eaſie to get, as hard to keepe. With theſe few lines then I purpoſe to doe rather the office of a friend then of a flatterer, and no whit to diſguiſe the truth vnto you, deſiring you as from a true and honeſt friend to take this aduertiſement, which ſhall bring you if not much commodity, at leaſt wiſe much honor and credit, and I doubt not if you haue that iudgement yet remaining, which I haue promiſed to my ſelfe out of the ability of your ſpirit, but you will acknowledge that euerie pettie honour is to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the greateſt profit. It apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb facs="tcp:2723:35"/> to the office, not of a meane creature, but of a cruell and inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, to follow that profeſſion you doe, by ſéeking the death of men, and conuerting into their ruine that elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which nature for the good of the liuing hath ſo liberally imparted vnto you, and I know it cannot bée done without great offence vnto God. Who though hée bee very iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice it ſelfe, yet as ſingular and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable mercy, he enclines more to pittie and pardon, then to paine and puniſhment. And how can you without offence of his diuine maieſty ſo often call into iudgement, the life (it may be) of the innocent. Retire your ſelfe from this courſe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying your wit (the gift of God and nature) to a better vſe, make more account of reputation then wealth, which indéed is the onely motiue that carries you thereunto. For if you pleaſe, you cannot want many other good meanes both for the one and the other. I am conſtrained euen out of
<pb facs="tcp:2723:36"/> friendſhip, hearing the bad and in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous report that goes of you euerie where, &amp; that too accompanied with the danger of your life, to write thus plainely vnto you. I ſhould bée very glad if it could draw you from ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable a practiſe, and reſtore you your wonted reputation. Otherwiſe I pronounce you vnworthy of our friendſhip, &amp; deſire the world ſhould know that I loued you no longer then I ſaw you walking in the way of vertue. And ſo I bid you farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An expoſtulation of vnkind miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceipts and iealouſies in friendſhip.</head>
               <p>SIr, Your wiſdome well known of al, and approued vnto many, with the experience I haue made of it, would neuer haue ſuffered me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that which was often deliuered vnto me by the letters of my friends,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:36"/> had I not vnderſtood as much by the laſt I receiued from you, more fraught with choller then reaſon. I cannot imagine how a man of ſuch knowledge, and more iudgement, brought vp in Court, and continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie employed in affairs, ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to an opinion of me, ſo far from truth, and the bent of my diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which hath euer béene moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to make good vnto the world in what eſtéem I haue alwaies held the friendſhip of ſo worthy a gentleman as your ſelfe. You may be perſwaded then I neuer committed any thing againſt you, which might any way offend the reputation of an honeſt and vertuous man, and thereof I wiſh no better teſtimony then mine owne thoughts. Of all actions ſome be voluntary, and ſome neceſſarie. If my will ſhen haue neuer drawne me to offend you, nor any neceſſity how great ſoeuer it were, would euer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to wring our ancient friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, would you haue me giue credit
<pb facs="tcp:2723:37"/> to the perfidious and wicked impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of men, or (by your fauour) to ſome light and inconſiderate ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that poſſeſſeth you, rather then to mine owne conſcience. Nay ſir, be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured I am your friend, and that I deſerue you ſhould be mine yet more then you are, deſiring you that héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you will neither doe iniurie to the integritie of my nature, nor your owne diſcretion, vnleſſe that (weary of me, and oppreſſed with my vnſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceableneſſe and inutilities) you will make this an occaſion to cleere your hands of me, which at all times would appeare moſt vnworthy your iudgement and my deſert.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Conſolation for the death of a Brother or other friend.</head>
               <p>GOod Sir, I feare this Letter will worke effects contrarie to my deſire, and in ſtead of drying vp
<pb facs="tcp:2723:37"/> your teares, raiſe vp new ſtormes of heauineſſe in vs both, vpon diſcourſe of your brothers ſo vnexpected and much to be lamented death, I haue put off the doing of this office vntill now, as well in regard of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine owne ſorrow, which would not ſuffer me to write, as alſo in that I attended a conuenient time when as the extremitie of yours ſhould be ſo qualified, that it might giue way to that little comfort I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to miniſter vnto you. But how ſhould I offer you comfort, when as I haue as much or more neede of it then your ſelfe? For if he were your brother, he was my very deare and ſingular friend: if hee were kinde to you, he was much more to mee: for his affection to you was deriued from nature and bloud, but to mee out of election and will. He alwaies em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced you with an extraordinarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe hee was thereunto bound: but vpon me he conferred all offices of loue and liberalitie which I
<pb facs="tcp:2723:38"/> neuer deſerued. Let vs then with one conſent lament our infinite loſſe, and not only ours, but euerie mans that delighted in vertue and honour. Poore gentleman! when hee was in greateſt expectation of gathering the fruit which his vertues had promiſed him, like a freſh and new blowen roſe, euen in the entrance to his beſt daies, to bee cut off by the vnluckie hand of vntimely death! Howbeit, this is no little comfort, that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this world with the hope hee had giuen his friends of his vertues, with the fruit whereof he was a deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to his parents, with the honour he expected from his Countrie, and with the good he had promiſed al good men, leauing nothing behinde him but ſorrow and teares, and a deſire alwaies to bewaile him, alwaies to wiſh for him. He that loued him not, neuer knew him: he that knew him, and was not ſorrie for him, had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe nor humanitie. But what doe I meane to be carried away thus
<pb facs="tcp:2723:38"/> by griefe from my purpoſed end? Let vs leaue all ſorrow, and rather enuious of his ſelicitie, then mooued with his loſſe, let vs reioice at his fortune. He hath paid the debt which he ought vnto nature, and the ſooner it was, the better, was his hap. For happier is he that by an impetuous, but proſperous gale is ſpeedily dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into the deſired port, then he that arriues there with a long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous calme. And be that knew this life was but lent him of nature, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo, as hee was not vnwilling to die; if hee may be ſaid to die, that is gone out of darkneſſe into light, that leaues paine for pleaſure, and puts off mortalitie to become immortall. Wherein could the fauour of God appeare vnto him more, then in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him out of the troubles and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of this wicked world, before hee ſhould know the dangers of times, the ſorrowes of age, and the many miſchiefes that continually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on this miſerable life of ours?
<pb facs="tcp:2723:39"/> And well was it foreſéene of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that féeling it ſelfe cloied with the falſe and tranſitorie pleaſures of the earth, for to bee poſſeſſed of the true and euerlaſting idies of heauen, made him leaue vs, euen then when in the very prime and flouriſh of his yéeres he had attained to as much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and fame, as man with long trauell aſ bodie and minde could in al his life time acquire. But why, Sir, doe I take all this paines to finde out meanes of conſolation for you, that with much more eloquence and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is better able to comfort me, and that with more courage and conſtancie knowes how to beare this brunt of fortune? I will therefore ceaſe to be a further trouble either to you or my ſelfe, and with this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurance end, that as reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in his glorie he is now aſſuredly liuing in heauen, ſo ſhall the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his vertues haue an eternall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſpéech of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:39"/>
               <head>A complement ful of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies receiued.</head>
               <p>SIr, with many fauours, as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually you do, you may augment my obligation; but you cannot adde any thing to the loue I beare you, or the deſire I haue to do you ſeruice: for neither the one nor the other can be greater. And would the time could accommodate me as wel with means to ſatiſfie theſe debts, as it giues you occaſion to increaſe them. I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to you in much, and my abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is very ſmall; but it ſhalbe better; if like a rich and liberall Creditour, you will bee contented to take kinde words and the good affection of an honeſt heart in paiment of your cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies. I haue receiued <hi>M. G.</hi> his Letter, which you ſent mee, vnto whom (if you pleaſe) returne the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed anſwer: with that one office you ſhall gratifie two friends, and of
<pb facs="tcp:2723:40"/> them two if it were poſſible, make me alwaies more readie than I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>To be commanded by you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A graue interceſſion to a father for a ſonne that hath offended: with friendly teſtimonie of his hopefull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my reuerend friend M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, the friendſhip which hath béen betwixt vs from our youth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands mee to write the preſent, for to aduertiſe you how your ſonne <hi>R.</hi> doth euery day more and more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie himſelfe to the courſe you deſire of his ſtudies. I would not beleeue that which my boies reported of him, but ſounded him my ſelfe vpon the ſudden in his leſſon. And if the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:2723:40"/> ſaying bee true, that the Deare is knowen by his tract, I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you as much contentment from him as you wiſh. Wherfore I would counſell you (forgetting matters paſt) heereafter to embrace his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, like a louing father. All that I labour in, is to become caution to you both: to you, that hee ſhall be ſo good a ſonne, that as in age, ſo in well doing hee ſhall goe before the reſt of his brothers and ſiſters: to him, that hence forward you ſhall fauour him, not only as your eldeſt, but as your beſt beloued. It is no ſmall victorie for you, to haue ſubdued and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him according to your deſire, to ſtudie, after he had for a time follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed armes, whereunto he ſéemed to be naturally inclined: neither was it a leſſe victorie for him to haue ſubdued himſelfe for to obey you. And in truth you reape no little commoditie by his fault, in that now you know how good a ſonne you haue. Such as in the holy Scripture were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:41"/> and afterwards truly repented them, were no leſſe eſtéemed of God, nay many times more than thoſe which had not ſinned at all. I will not ſtand vpon any application, but commending both it and my ſelfe vnto you, very kindly take my leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A ſhort complement vpon receit of ſome new courteſie.</head>
               <p>SIr, I haue receiued the Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound you ſent me, wherewithall I am as much pleaſed, as hee was kindly deriued: although I muſt confeſſe, that in receiuing him I was ſomewhat aſhamed, by reaſon I thought this new courteſie did vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid me with my not acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet in action, how much I am your ſeruant in will. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I thanke you very kindly for him, and with ſuch affection, as hee
<pb facs="tcp:2723:41"/> that amongſt your friends moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to appeare how readie hee is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to vndergoe your commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and commend your liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as much as all your other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are aboue all your like generally commended. And ſo for this time I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Excuſe for too rare writing: vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging withall the proſecution of ſome buſineſſe: and vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the death of a friend, the election of another in his ſtead.</head>
               <p>SIr, you may perceiue by my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, that although I am your debter for many Letters, yet am I nothing behinde to you in good will: and the more my ſlacknes is in that, the more is my readineſſe to ſerue you in great matters. I am to deſire
<pb facs="tcp:2723:42"/> you to ſecond the requeſt I haue made vnto <hi>M. H.</hi> your vnkle and my very good friend concerning the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wherof I haue now written to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is verie eaſie for him, and without meanes impoſſible for mée to effect. The death of <hi>M. P.</hi> your kinſman very much troubled mee at the firſt, but I conſider that with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and reputation hee hath ſatiſfied God, his Prince, and the debt which he ought vnto nature. And no doubt but hee is now at peace in heauen, whereas we amidſt the troubles and corruptions of the world, are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually toſſed with the tribulations of this miſerable life. And ſéeing it hath pleaſed God to take from mee ſo good and faithfull a friend, I beſéech you to accept of the election I make of you in his ſtead, with ſuch a minde and affection to ſerue and honour you, as I haue alwaies carried to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. May you bee pleaſed then to receiue me into this degrée, and though my qualities deſerue it
<pb facs="tcp:2723:42"/> not, at leaſtwiſe it appertaines to the innated courteſie of your diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I aſſure my ſelfe that the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters héere incloſed ſhall finde ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe as their directions require, and that you will be pleaſed (if the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be in towne) to returne their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers. I will ſay no more, but only intreat you to loue me, and to write often vnto me, to the end that the gaine I make of you, may giue mee leſſe ſenſe of the loſſe I haue made of ſo deare a friend: and ſo very kindly I bid you farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:43"/>
               <head>Thankful acceptance of a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie counſell, aduiſing to follow (or ſerue) ſome greate man: whence ariſeth an obſeruation of the cold recompence of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices in theſe daies in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of times paſt.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my truly louing friend.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, you were not out of reaſon when like a friend for to comfort me in my troubles, or rather indéed to poſſeſſe mee with that care which euery man ought to haue of the time to come. You told me I ſhould doe well to put my ſelfe into the ſeruice of ſome great perſonage, where you were perſwaded I ſhould be well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, and that the ſooner it were the better it would be, nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more precious than time. Your
<pb facs="tcp:2723:43"/> counſell ſéemes to mee without all queſtion no leſſe vertuous and wiſe, than worthy of our friendſhip; and I am fully reſolued to follow it. But the feare of not attaining that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded end, is as it were a very croſſe to my reſolution. For the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the time is ſuch, that one is more deceiued in the recompence of ſeruices, than in any other practiſes whatſoeuer. Great men thinke that others inferiour to them in fortunes were expreſly made for their onely and particular reſpect, neuer conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that if they would put that fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall opinion out of their heads, they ſhould with much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment be better ſerued. <hi>M. Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> hauing many ſeruants, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies very carefull of them, and with all gentleneſſe vſed them no worſe than his owne children. One of the chiefeſt ſatiſfactions that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> in his end, was, that hee had well acknowledged the merit of his ſeruants. But the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor
<pb facs="tcp:2723:44"/> of theſe ancient vertues is now to ſéeke, and to ſerue with loſſe and preiudice is become euen a matter of neceſſitie. Let not the ſpurre of your affection then poſt mee on ſo faſt to a ſeruice, that I repent me but too late of my more haſte than good ſpéede. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe it is againſt my nature to bee idle, I will doe as God ſhall put in my minde, hoping to meet with the fortune of ſome good <hi>Craſſus;</hi> and to that effect let mée bée remembred in your praiers, as your proſperity ſhal dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie finde a place for it in mine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:44"/>
               <head>Vpon ſubmiſſion of a runnagate and vnruly ſonne, the kinde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (vnder hand) commends him to the ſeruice of a worthy friend, vnder whoſe ſhelter neceſſitie had alreadie driuen him.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my very honourable friend Sir R. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, hauing alwaies honoured and reſpected you among other my worthy friends, not onely for your vertues, but for a certaine kinde of I know not what obligation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which inuites me thereunto, I perſwade my ſelfe that you alſo haue ſome inſtinct and naturall inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good will towards me. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I am drawen with the more boldneſſe to offer you a requeſt I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much deſire to obtaine. I am a
<pb facs="tcp:2723:45"/> father; when I ſay father, you may withall imagine the tyrannie which nature exerciſeth ouer mee in fauour of my children. It hath pleaſed God to giue me fiue ſonnes, of the which I had deſtined the third to the ſeruice of the Court: but as it commonly failes out, that fathers purpoſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for their children, and they diſpoſe of them contrary to their mindes, ſo it happened that he whom I ſpake of ſtole out of <hi>England</hi> without my knowledge, about thrée moneths a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, and croſſing into <hi>France,</hi> came at length to <hi>Paris,</hi> where his meanes failing him, he hath bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and begins to repreſent the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the prodigall childe vnto his father, which I am very well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to accompliſh. Hee hath craued pardon of me by Letters, and by the ſame meane interpoſed the authority of a kinſman of mine one <hi>M. M.</hi> a gentleman of quality, who hath béen theſe two yéeres abroad in trauell. I vnderſtand hee hath done his dutie
<pb facs="tcp:2723:45"/> vnto you, and that you haue kindly entertained him, vpon knowledge that hee was my ſonne. Now ſince his fortune hath carried him thither, I ſhall humbly entreat ſo much fauor of you, as to take him into your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, with no other priuiledge then as one of the meaneſt in your houſe. So doing, you ſhall get two ſeruants at once, the one there with you in <hi>Paris,</hi> and the other to receiue your commandements in <hi>England.</hi> If you can be pleaſed to ſatiſfie me herein, I wiſh hee ſhould thinke it were done not at any inſtance of mine, but only out of your gentlenes, ſéeing him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to that extremity which in my iudgement he is in, whatſoeuer ſhew hee makes. I hope if you vouchſafe to doe him this honor, being in ſuch a ſchoole, his debauſche will turn to his good. But howſoeuer my entreaties run they ſhal be alwaies limited with that ſaying of <hi>Cicero. <hi>Quod commodo tuo facere poſſis.</hi>
                  </hi> I make no queſtion but there are others that preſſe you
<pb facs="tcp:2723:46"/> with ſuch ſuites, but none that haue ſo much deſire to doe you all ſeruice as my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Excuſe for not comming to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate a friends returne: with proteſtation and compariſon of affection with the forwardeſt.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my worthy reſpected friend M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, it would haue béene a point of my duty to haue come in perſon for to haue welcommed you home. But ſéeing my affaires will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it, I haue ſent the preſent to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that office, and to let you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that albeit there bée many which for their vertuous qualities do better deſerue your loue, yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:2723:46"/> of my affection, and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deſire I haue to ſerue and honour you, there is none more worthy of it than my ſelfe. And though you are to hope for more riches of ſpirit and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune from them, than from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty of my vnderſtanding &amp; eſtate: yet are you not to prefer their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip vnto mine. For if they outreach mée in merit, I will go beyond them in good will, and if the abilities of their mind bée more, the ſincerity of their heart ſhall bée leſſe. But héerein you are to imitate the liberall, who with a frank and gentle will imparts of his fauours to euery neceſſity; not as a vſurer to make profit of them, but onely out of a kind and generous diſpoſition; So it is then you ſhould bee affected towards mée, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expectation of other aduantage by it, than my ſeruice, and you are to doe it the rather, in that you feel your ſelfe ſo noble, rich, and vertuous, that whatſoeuer you can deſire or wiſh for in another, is aboundantly in
<pb facs="tcp:2723:47"/> your owne poſſeſſion, and you haue as little néede of fortaine vertnes, as the ſea hath of the water of little ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Héereupon I will leaue to be a further trouble vnto you, but not to aſſure you, that I deſire to liue no longer than I ſhall deſire</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>To ſerue you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Thankfull acknowledgement of kindneſſe vnto ones Sonne.</head>
               <p>SIr, the fauours you haue latelie done me are of ſuch effect and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that I ſhall neuer be at quiet till I haue made ſome requitall of them. I am aſhamed you ſhould be ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with this ſonne of mine, whom I haue charged to obey you in all things as my ſelfe, and I pray you doe ſo much as haue an eye vpon him as if you were his Father. I thanke you very kindly for the apparell you haue made him, and the money you
<pb facs="tcp:2723:47"/> haue paied for him: you may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate him with the reſt of it as you ſhall thinke good. For, for my part, I giue you all power ouer him, ſéeing you are pleaſed to take the trouble vpon you, and ſo wiſhing but to méet with ſome good occaſion to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how much I am beholding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I commit you to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A priuate taxation of the publike ingratitude of great perſons toward ſuch as haue beſt deſerued of them.</head>
               <p>SIr, Wheras you think it ſtrange that I write no oftner vnto the Lady you wot of: I haue alwaies told you, and now tell you again that which I was wont to ſay of great Lords, at ſuch time as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it at my hands, that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their greatneſſe and reputation
<pb facs="tcp:2723:48"/> no longer, than they are mindfull of my neceſſities. Hée that makes no reckoning of me, teaches me to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect him, &amp; he that looks vpon me with reſpect, giues me occaſion and deſire to ſerue him: ſo that I alwaies goe as others goe, and no otherwiſe. You may alledge the many commodities of their fauour and countenance, and I may anſwer that it were an idle thing for me to trouble my head with a matter I am not ſenſible of. <hi>Do vt des, facio vt facias;</hi> ſaies the loue of Lawers: but hauing done ſo many ſeruices, and neuer receiued ſo much as a taſte of liberality, is the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a water able to quench the fire of an hundred <hi>Aetnaes,</hi> much more to diſcourage mée, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe am moſt readie by all offices of courteſie to kéepe the good will of ſuch as pleaſe to honor me with the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of which number, to you, as to one of the moſt eſpecial, with all affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I commend mee, and bid you farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:48"/>
               <head>Excuſe for not ſaluting a friend paſſing by vs: endeuouring (by the way) to wipe away his imputation of pride and of forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</head>
               <p>SIr, you told my Coſen that either I was growne proud, or had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten you, becauſe I paſſed along by you the other day, and did not ſpeake. Now this I perceiue was the cauſe why you came not along with the reſt of the company to honour mée with your preſence. But you ſhall vnderſtand that when I met you, I was ſo farre out of patience with the ingratitude of a wicked friend, which was newly parted from me, that I continued a whole wéeke together without the remembrance not onely of you, but my ſelfe: which together with the knowledge you are to haue of my naturall humors, may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb facs="tcp:2723:49"/> excuſe me to either of your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. Beſides, I could not forget a Gentleman well deriued, happily married, liuing with all modeſty of his owne, a friend to euery man, not medling nor making with any, one that is contented with his eſtate, loues vertue and the vertuous, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away his time with choice of good companie, is perfect in mind and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, but of body (to my great griefe) ſomwhat weak and indiſpoſed. Now iudge, Sir, whether I remember you or no, and be no longer perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that either I am proud, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of you: whoſe many courteſies haue bound me to be alwaies.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your affectionate friend and Seruant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:49"/>
               <head>A ſad commemoration of ſome worthy friend deceaſed.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my ſingular good friend. M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, the griefe of my kinſmans death hath gotten ſo much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in my apprehenſion that the comfort I was wont to giue vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is not able now to doe my ſelfe any ſeruice. Reaſon diſſwades mee from ſorrow, and ſenſe prouokes mée to teares: my power is ſmall, the frailty of the fleſh great. I deſire to obey vnto the one, the other I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſiſt: ſo that in the ſedition of ſo many contrati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties, I neither vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand nor ſée any thing may content mée. In regard of him I haue no cauſe to complaine: he lead the life of a good man, and died the death of the righteous: for as the Romane Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſaith, It is hard to liue well and
<pb facs="tcp:2723:50"/> dye ill. But for my part I haue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much reaſon to lament as his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues were without number and end. Howbeit if for mine owne particular I ſhould grieus, wheras for his I am much to reioyce, I ſhal be thought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enuious of his good, then a friend of his happines. I aſſure my ſelfe alſo that you take no pleaſure in the death of ſo curteons and worthy a Gntleman, nor in the loſſe you haue made of one, that for your owne good parts and my ſake, loued you as a friend, and reſpected you as vertuous But not to bée a cauſe either of more trouble to you, or heauineſſe to my ſelfe, I will ceaſe to ſpeake fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to God ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kindly take my leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:50"/>
               <head>A gratefull acknowledgement of an eſpeciall fauour from any great man.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my very Honourable good Lord the Lord &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY Lord I haue receiued the commendations you were ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſed to ſend mee by my brother <hi>C.</hi> than the which there is no fauour I could more deſire. Henceforward I ſhall begin to think better of my ſelfe ſéeing ſo noble and honourable a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath thought mee worthy of a place in his remembrance: which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth was more requiſite for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of your goodneſſe, then for any merit at all of mine. Howſoeuer I giue your Lordſhip as humble thanks for it as poſſibly I may, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it I am perſwaded that neither with words nor effects I ſhall euer bée able
<pb facs="tcp:2723:51"/> to ſatiſfy ſo great an obligatiou. This fauor hath cleared mee of ſome doubt I was in, for that I receiued no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the letter I wrote not long ſince, in congratulation of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſo deſerued aduancements, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with an humble preſentation of my ſeruices: but now I perceiue the cauſe of it procéeded either from the fault of your Secretary, or the negligence of the poſt being alwaies well aſſured that no greatnes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer could elate your mind more then it would be deiected by any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity the worſt of time could bring. I haue nothing to adde hereunto but an humble entreaty, that as you were pleaſed to remember mee with your commendations, ſo you would vouchſafe to honour mee with your commandements, thereby to giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the deſire I alwaies haue of appearing vnto the world how much I am.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Vnfainedly deuoted to your ſeruice.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:51"/>
               <head>A ſhort and ſweet conſolation in the death of Friends.</head>
               <p>SIr, as ſoone as I vnderſtood of the death of <hi>M. G.</hi> I began to thinke of you, and how many times I had ſayd to my ſelfe, ſéeing you alwaies in company together, like the ſigne of <hi>Gemini,</hi> behold an example of true and perfect friendſhip. But ſince it hath pleaſed heauen to diuide you: I would wiſh you to beare it with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and be comforted. For wée are not to grieue at who goes firſt or laſt in the way which euery man is to take by a neceſſity of nature. The world is a reſidence lent vs by the good pleaſure of God, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues leaſt in it, is the longer liuing in happineſſe. For death doth deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in life, ſo ſoone as a righteous ſpirit doth leaue that priſon, wherein all the miſeries imagination can reach vnto are incloſed. What is
<pb facs="tcp:2723:52"/> there to be ſéene héere vpon earth, but enuy, iniuſtice, ambition, ſtrife, but good manners corrupted into barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conditions, children &amp; gréefe, to rich, a care to poore parents, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire for to haue vnto thoſe that haue none? What is there to bée ſéene but peace engendring war, war ſhedding bloud, ſoueraignty a pray to ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſubiection the ſlaue of miſery and deſpaire, pouerty deſpiſed, riches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, youth puffed vp with rage and inſolency, and age oppreſſed with infirmity and diſeaſes? wherfore the beſt is not to be at al, or not to be long in the way, prouided that it all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céed from the good will of God, whom I humbly beſéech to giue you that comfort and content I alwaies wiſh you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:52"/>
               <head>A modeſt complement extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our owne deſert in any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour done our friend, acknowledging all to be but dutie.</head>
               <p>SIr, I ſée no reaſon why by your letters you ſhould thanke mée for the pleaſures you ſay you haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of me, vnleſſe it be to encourage me that haue béen but ſlack that way héeretofore to doe better héereafter. To ſay the truth, it procéeds from no merit of mine, but from a courteſie that was born with you, and will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company you to your graue. For, for my part I doe not thinke one can bée beholding to a man for doing his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If you pleaſe then you ſhall not put theſe thanks vnto account, but turne them into commandements: vpon him that will alwaies moſt gladly employ himſelfe for you and
<pb facs="tcp:2723:53"/> yours induced thereunto both by the friendſhip that hath euer béene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs, and a thouſand other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities, the recitall wherof would but waſt time and paper. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you write that you feare you are troubleſome vnto mee, conſidering the greatneſſe of my affairs: the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt trouble I can haue, is when I ſhall not be troubled for you, if at any time you haue occaſion to vſe mee, as ſhall be approoued to your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in all matters where the leaſt of my abilities may doe you ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:53"/>
               <head>A gentle and eaſie ſubmiſſion to ſome new direction or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the right honourable my eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall good Lord and Maſter The Lord &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY honourable Lord, your laſt of the fourth of Iulie came not before this morning to my hands, whereby I vnderſtand the change of your minde concerning my voyage into <hi>France:</hi> and although for mine owne particular I could haue wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it otherwiſe, yet reaſon perſwades me to be contented, aſſuring my ſelfe that this reuocation is deriued from ſome better reſolution. Wherefore I had rather my deſires ſhould want their end, than your pleaſure, that your L. may alwaies know I hold
<pb facs="tcp:2723:54"/> more of modeſty and diſcretion, than of appetite and will, and that mine owne ſatiſfactions are nothing to the reſpect of your greatnes and ſeruice. Aſſoone as I receiued your diſpatch, I began to negotiate about the other matter, and by the next your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhall vnderſtand what may bée done. In the meane time and euer I remaine</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your honours very humble and faithfull ſeruant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Recommendation of a forward ſonne to the fauour and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſome famous Captaine in the warres.</head>
               <p>SIr, albeit it were reaſon that your not knowing me ſhould frée you from the trouble of my Letters, yet
<pb facs="tcp:2723:54"/> ſince it hath pleaſed Sir <hi>William I.</hi> to recommend my ſonne vnto you, I thought I ſhould haue wronged my dutie, if I had not accompanied him with the preſent. I haue deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to the warres, and hée hath béene about ſome thrée yéeres abroad in trauell, during which time hée hath giuen himſelfe vnto diuers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exerciſes well be fitting his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. At his returne I thought if hee could receiue ſo much honour as to be fauoured by you, hee might fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate a way for the time to come, which euery good and valiant minde is to propound vnto it ſelfe. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know that you are the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of vertue, not onely in the ſubiect of Armes, but in euery other, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech you to reſpect him as the ſonne of a father, that excéedingly deſires to find a place in the number of your humble and moſt deuoted ſeruants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:55"/>
               <head>A Complement moſt officious and affectionate to a Lady concerning ſome ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affaires of hers.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the noble and euery way ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MAdam, I had rather effects ſhould teſtifie the deſire I haue to doe you ſeruice, than the courteſie of that good gentleman <hi>M. B.</hi> for ſo ſhould I both ſerue you and ſatiſfie my ſelfe, whereas by the other nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs reapes any commoditie at all. You are no way beholding to me for ſolliciting my Lord of <hi>N.</hi> or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sir <hi>George L.</hi> in minde of your affaires. For to the one you haue no néed of recommendation, nor to the
<pb facs="tcp:2723:55"/> other of remembrance. The former (according to his noble inclination) much reſpects you, and deſires your honour and profit as much as his owne: and the other, as well to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my ſaid Lord, as for his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar obligation to your Ladiſhip, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for nothing more than occaſion to doe you pleaſure. It is not therefore in ſo ſmall a matter as that I deſire to obey you, but in things of ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie, as may ſhew how I am e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen couetous of receiuing your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</p>
               <p>I will ſay no more at this time, but wiſh my praiers could obtaine you ſuch fortunes as your vertues deſerue, and then I am ſure you ſhould be no leſſe than Empreſſe of the world. Only as I was making vp the preſent, this incloſed paper came to my hands, which I haue ſent you as a thing I know you would very faine ſée. After you haue read it, I muſt intreat, for ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, it may be committed to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie
<pb facs="tcp:2723:56"/> of the fire: and ſo in all dutie and affection I kiſſe your hand.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By the humble ſeruant of your commandements.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A pleaſant <hi>Ironie,</hi> in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Law, and the commodity of Law Suites.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my dearely beloued brother M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>GOod brother, I would neuer haue thought that a ſuit in law could haue brought ſo many bleſſings with it as it doth. Are you ſlothfull and lazie? make no doubt but you ſhall finde matter enough to kéepe you from idleneſſe: you néed no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:2723:56"/> a raiſer of you vp in a morning than a ſuit. Are you proud and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull? I warrant you ſhall haue ſufficient cauſe to court not onely the Iudges, but your Counſell and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, nay by my faith their very Clerke. If of a dull and heauie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, you ſhall méet with ſtore of inuention how to kéepe you out of your enemies danger. If ſhamefaſt, neceſſitie will teach you rather to bée impudent than otherwiſe. If coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, no helpe for it in the world like this: for there is no commoditie in the land beares ſuch a price as the law doth. A man is to paſſe thorow ſo many hands, and euery finger ketcheth ſomewhat. Beſides for the deſire wee haue to obtaine our ends, we neuer thinke what it will coſt vs, till we come to the bottome of our purſes. I am ſure I haue made deare experience of all this. And they are great bleſſings I muſt néeds ſay, but God kéepe you from them. Well I haue ieſted enough, it is time for me
<pb facs="tcp:2723:57"/> now to tell you in good earneſt that I thinke there is no paſſion more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or that fils our heads ſo full of proclamations as this doth. I will not except the three torments of our ſpirit, loue, ambition, and auarice: for in this there is a mixture of the two laſt, accompanied with a deſire of reuenge, which produceth very maruellous effects in vs. The Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian ſaith, that no man knowes what pleaſure it is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged, but he that hath receiued the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:57"/>
               <head>A prettie controuerſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in a wittie complement.</head>
               <p>SIr, I know not whether I ſhould excuſe the ſlackneſſe of my pen, or accuſe your negligence. For my part, the trouble of my continuall emploiment, well knowen both to you and euery man, may iuſtly cléere me of this fault: but the leaſure and good commoditie you alwaies haue to write, cannot free you from blame. Neuertheleſſe, not to caſt away our money in ſuits, which you know are euerlaſting, full of hazard, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the inconſtancie, ambition, and wickedneſſe of the moſt part of the Lawyers of theſe times, I am contented to ſtand to the iudgement of your owne conſcience; or if you will, like good Merchants that haue cléered accounts, let vs make gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall releaſes, ſo that neither ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine debtor to the other. But if
<pb facs="tcp:2723:58"/> you will néeds goe to Law, I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréed: for hauing reaſon for my At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, and truth for counſell in my cauſe, if by the power of bribes you corrupt not the Iudges, I doubt not but to haue a verdict of my ſide. Now of theſe two waies I leaue the beſt to your election: aſſuring you, that albeit you haue ouercome mee with offices of courteſie, yet haue you not gone beyond mee either in loue or iudgement, to know that I owe more to your good will than euer I ſhall be able to furniſh. But if an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt minde alone could ſerue for pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo many obligations, make account I ſhould eaſily ſatiſfie grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter debts than theſe. Whereupon I inuoke the grace of time that may bring me ſome ſuch opportunitie, as may thorowly approoue the ſinceritie of my heart to your experience. In the meane ſpace let mee intreat you to giue mee occaſion to doe you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: for I cannot receiue a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement from any friend vnto whom
<pb facs="tcp:2723:58"/> I more deſire to obey than your ſelfe, with the aſſurance whereof I will héere conclude, and commit you to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A briefe anſwer to a bitter Complaint vpon a falſe ground.</head>
               <p>SIr, I am ſorrie for the wrong you doe your ſelfe in complaining of mée without cauſe. I thought we ſhould haue ſéene you héere in the Countrie ere this, and it gréeues me you came not, as well in regard I haue loſt the occaſion to giue you the entertainment of my houſe, as that I might haue fréed you from this paſſion of profit which ſo detaines you from diſcerning the truth. But ſince I cannot doe it in perſon, you are to vnderſtand by this paper, that I haue nothing to doe now in the Office where you are aſſigned the
<pb facs="tcp:2723:59"/> paiment of your penſion. I haue paſt it ouer vnto another who can giue you ſatiſfaction if hée will. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue no reaſon to ſay you will plaine of mée, ſeeing I haue done nothing but that I ſhould. If this will not content you, within ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or eight daies at the fartheſt, I ſhall bée at <hi>London,</hi> where we may meet, and conferre more at large of matters. In the meane time commending me vnto you, I commit you to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:59"/>
               <head>An earneſt and elegant intreaty, importuning the aſſiſtance of ſome friend in any matter of importance, and that with expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my honourable friend Sir Henry T.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, I will beginne with the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Marcus Cicero,</hi> becauſe I perſwade my ſelfe that the authoritie of ſuch perſonages, and the efficacie of their words will bée of more power and eſtéeme with you than mine: although to incite you to any office of courteſie, whereunto a naturall addiction makes you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough of your ſelfe, I cannot thinke there is néede of more than a bare and ſimple intreatie. <hi>Man</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is not borne for himſelfe alone,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:60"/> but for his Countrey, for his parents, for his friends, and for all other men.</hi> And euen as Nature, the vniuerſall Mother of all things created, doth not produce ſo many kinds of beaſts, herbes, trées, fruits, metals and ſtones for her ſelfe onely, but fréely imparts vnto vs of thoſe her riches: ſo we that are to imitate her liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, muſt not bée ſparing of thoſe abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and meanes which either for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune or our owne vertue hath acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs for the good and reléefe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This being ſo, I cannot doubt that you, in whom is ſuch a concurrence of excellent parts, will bée wanting to the neceſſitie of my preſent affaire. And albeit the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of my deſerts, the integritie of my heart, the reſpect of my ſeruices, and other points appertaining to the iudgement of liberalitie, cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you thereunto, yet let the loue and obedience I haue euer born you, ſupplie all other defects. But that my Letter may not runne out all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:2723:60"/> preface, nor you be wearied with the long narration of a matter well enough knowen to you alreadie, I will referre the reſt to the ſufficiencie and truſt of <hi>M. H.</hi> For ſéeing you vnderſtand my occaſion, I muſt hope you will bée pleaſed to take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for it, as with much facilitie and very commodiouſly you may. And becauſe that obtaining this grace, if withall, expedition bée not made, it would bee as good as time loſt: may it pleaſe you, hauing taken vpon you the one, to vndergoe the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the other, which will bée of that import in my behalfe, that bée aſſured I ſhall bée your perpetuall debtor for it, notwithſtanding any ſatiſfaction in the world I can euer bée able to make. Sir <hi>Richard G.</hi> in the exerciſe of this fauour, as in all other generous actions, will not faile to ſecond you, ſince I am ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to doe very humble ſeruice to you both, and to you eſpecially, and that with all honour, reſpect, and as
<pb facs="tcp:2723:61"/> much affection, as I earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech the Almightie to adde many yéeres of proſperitie to your preſent happineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A kinde quarrell of vnkindneſſe with a friend for leauing vs vnſeene and vnſaluted hauing in a manner paſſed by our doore.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my approoued good friend M. Richard. T.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY beſt friend your departure from <hi>M.</hi> contrary to my hope and your determination hath not ſo much diſpleaſed mee, for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you know of, as in that you paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed along ſo cloſe by mee, without taking poſſeſſion of a houſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:2723:61"/> that, that depends on it, which is as much at your commandement as the very thoughts of your heart, but eſpecially in that you let flip an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to experience how much I deſire to acknowledge the many kindneſſes I haue receiued from you: Howbeit ſéeing it was your pleaſure ſo to doe, theſe letters ſhall make faith of my good will, farre rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to any thing that concerns your reputation or profit, than to write. By this time I beleeue you haue heard from my Gentleman, who it may bee will ſhew himſelfe ſo much my friend as to make me ſue for my money, if it be ſo, I pray tell him I would not wiſh him to giue me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that whereas now I talke to him inpriuate, I ſhould complaine of him in publike. For there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I ſhould ſuffer preiudice by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers ingratitude. I haue ſent you héere incloſed the letter I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto him vnſealed, that you may read it and then make it vp, hoping
<pb facs="tcp:2723:62"/> notwithſtanding that you haue ſo preuailed with him, as hee ſhall not néede to ſée it. If you know any thing wherein I may ſerue you, I ſhall alwaies bee more willing to obey, then you to command. To the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance whereof I leaue you, and my ſelfe to bée</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Euer truely your friend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:62"/>
               <head>Interceſſion for fauour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the behalfe of one that hath offended, and is vnfeignedly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for his fault.</head>
               <p>SIr, not being able (as I had well hoped) to obtaine any fauour of my Lord: for in the behalf of the poore fellow, I thought good to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto your interceſſion for him Hee is ſo penitent and fully reſolued to become a new man, that this good purpoſe of amendment in him, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the puniſhment of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durance, is worthy not onely of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, but of pardon for his fault. If héerein you doe that which I could not, you ſhall bind me to a continuall endeuor to deſerue it: and the time may come my Lord may thanke you for the meanes you ſhall giue him to exerciſe mercy and gentlenes, which
<pb facs="tcp:2723:63"/> ſhould be conformable to the many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther noble qualities ouer in him.</p>
               <p>I ſend you héere incloſed the latin verſes, which by your commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I haue apparelled in Engliſh, and that too I aſſure you with the beſt clothes in my ſhop: but if they be not fitting to the greatnes of their quality, I commend them to the Wardrobe of your moſt pretious ornaments, and you to the protection of the Almighty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:63"/>
               <head>To importune a friend to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute to perfection any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe already begun.</head>
               <p>SIr, I finde ſo much difficulty in the officers about the payment of the money, it hath pleaſed my Lord to beſtow on me, that if you had not béene the mediator of this liberality, I feare I ſhould haue gone without. Wherefore I beſéech you, as before you were the meanes for the grant of it, ſo now you would be the meanes for the payment of it: Which will bee the eaſier for you to doe, in that the former depended on the will of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and this of your owne. I cannot be beholding to you for the one without the other, for it will bée to no purpoſe if they be not ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. I humbly entreat you then to doe it, as you are bound both to the goodnes of your owne diſpoſition ſtill enclining to the ayd of your friends,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:64"/> and to me that haue alwaies deſired to do you ſeruice, as alſo to the world vnto whom it is not vnknown how much I haue euer loued and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted you. Let me not be deceiued in the hope I haue alwaies had of your fauor, eſpecially in a matter that will be very preiudiciall to mee, and no way pleaſing to my Lord. I will not preſſe you farther at this time, becauſe I am perſwaded that my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties cannot be of more power with you, then your own iudgement which knows what is fit for you to doe, and neceſſary for mée to haue done: So that committing you to that readines of will I haue euer found you accompanied with in all my occaſions, I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours alwaies as ready to ſerue you.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:64"/>
               <head>A particular account of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie buſineſſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ones care.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the Worſhipfull my very good Maſter M. R. S. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, may you bee pleaſed to take account of ſuch commandements as you charged mee withall at my comming vp: of the which to begin with the money due from <hi>M. B.</hi> I haue receiued it in, and paid it ouer héere, according to your direction in that caſe, to be repaid you againe in the Countrey: for the other bonds that are in ſuit, your Atturney pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth that faithfulneſſe and care which both you expect and he in duty is to haue. <hi>M. R.</hi> is not yet in town for there is not any day but I am at his lodging to enquire after him: to
<pb facs="tcp:2723:65"/> morrow or next day hee is expected, and hee ſhall bee no ſooner come but I will follow him very cloſe for a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of that buſineſſe. I know not well what to ſay to your ſuite with my Lord, euery day begets new dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, and I doubt ſome ſecret oppoſition from the party you ſpake of when laſt you diſcourſed vnto mée of this matter, and heerein, <hi>M. P.</hi> my Lords Secretary iumps with me in opinion, if it be ſo, he ſaith nothing will preuaile but your preſence, which if I ſhall find to bée néedfull I will ſo aduertiſe you by the next. Of thoſe things which I am to buy for my miſtriſſe ſo many as the time and my other employments would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to prouide, I haue ſent down now by this bearer, the reſt God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall come along with the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Héere is no newes at all ſtirring but ſuch idle ſtuffe as I would bée loth by a deliuery of it to hold you from your ſerious and better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:65"/>
               <p>Wherefore very humbly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending my duty to you, and my good miſtreſſe, I ceaſe to be a further trouble, and reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Alwaies your humble ſeruant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:66"/>
               <head>A moſt Chriſtian conſolation of a friend in any croſſe or affliction.</head>
               <p>SIr, I cannot doubt but you are perſwaded that the tribulations wherewithall we are afflicted in this life, doe not procéede from chance or fatall deſtiny, but from a ſpeciall prouidence of God, without the which, not ſo much as an haire can fall from any of our heads, as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> doth inſinuate, when hée ſaith, <hi>There is no euill in the City which I haue not ſent.</hi> This alſo is manifeſted in <hi>Iob,</hi> whom Satan could not touch without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion firſt obtained for it. Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are aſſured ſignes of election, ſo that if you obſerue the whole courſe of the Scriptures, you ſhall finde that thoſe whom God fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt, he alwaies gaue to drinke
<pb facs="tcp:2723:66"/> of the cup of his paſſion: witneſſe <hi>Abell,</hi> perſecuted by <hi>Cain, Iſaac</hi> by <hi>Iſmael, Ioſeph</hi> by his brethren, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> by <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> by <hi>Pharao.</hi> Out of a ſenſible conſideration whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, If we had no other hope in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, but in this preſent life, wee might well ſay wee were the moſt miſerable amongſt men. But the worſt that wee endure is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of that which God himſelfe endured: who though hee created all things was termed the ſonne of a Carpenter, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, was ſlandered, was ſaide to be a glutton, a drunkard, a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Publicanes and ſinners, a wicked ſeducer, and one that in the name of Béelzebub caſt out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills. If wee conſider what hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came for vs, wee ſhall ſée him naked to cloth vs, a priſoner and in bonds to looſe vs from the chaines of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and a ſacrifice to purifie vs: Wee ſhall ſée his ſide opened to
<pb facs="tcp:2723:67"/> ſhut vp hell for vs, wee ſhall ſée thoſe hands that made heauen and earth, pierced with ſharpe nailes for the loue of vs, and his head crowned with pricking thornes to crowne vs with glory. From his ſorrow comes our ioy, from his infirmity our ſtrength, from his death and buriall, our life and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Comfort your ſelfe then in the Lord, and with patience beare the Croſſes which it hath pleaſed him to lay vpon you, for his arme is not ſhortned, but in his good time will either take you from theſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or theſe miſeries from you. Now many vs there yet liuing in the world whom, oppreſſed with infinite cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, euery way forſaken, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly boide of all hope of ſuccour, he at length beheld with a merciful eye, and hath placed them in a farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more contented eſtate than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were in before. Wherefore truſt in God, and ſay with that great and holy martyr <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:67"/> let hangmen, let beaſts, and all the deuils in hell exerciſe their greateſt fury on mee, ſo that I may enioy the Lord my God, whom in all my prayers I will heartily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech to giue you a ſpeedy and happie iſſue out of all your troubles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:68"/>
               <head>An earneſt recommendation of a well qualified ſeruant, to ſome place worthy of his part.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my worthy and moſt expected friend M. &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, as long as you ſhall bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a deſire to oblige mee vnto you, by ſo many gentle offices of courteſie as continually you ſhew mée, I ſhall neuer want boldneſſe to giue you occaſion ſtill to doe it: and the rather, becauſe I know not any vnto whom I would more willingly be beholding then to ſo kinde and generous diſpoſition as yours. The preſent bearer <hi>Philip A.</hi> is more then ordinarily affected
<pb facs="tcp:2723:68"/> to your ſeruice, and knowing the loue and reſpect I beare you, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that my interpoſure will not bee a little auaileable in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, ſo that hee hath very earneſtly intreated mee out of my intereſt to make him a way to your fauour: and I haue vndertaken it, for that I make no queſtion but it will turne to his no little good, and your greater commodity. For he is a ciuil, diſcréet, and very honeſt young man, he hath his latin tongue perfect, ſpeakes Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, is pretily ſéene in the French, writes faire two or three hands, ſings well, playes on the vyall, and indéed is euery way better qualified than I deliuer him, as will appeare to your iudgement, vpon the examination you ſhall make of his parts, to the which I will referre him, and wiſh he may no leſſe excéede the hope I haue giuen you of him, than you the promiſe I haue made him of your goodneſſe. If I haue as much power with you, as the world thinks, and is
<pb facs="tcp:2723:69"/> due to the greatnes and integrity of my affection, I doubt not but to hear ere it be long, that this commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine is happily arriued at the port of his deſeri: Howſoeuer, my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty ſhould preſſe you further, were I not aſſured that you will think you are not to be importuned for one that of himſelfe is moſt worthy of regard and your entertainment. Wherefore to make an end of my ſure and your trouble, I will héere giue ende to the preſent, and allwaies be moſt deſirous to do you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:69"/>
               <head>An amorous complement vpon the firſt ſight, or after ſome ſhort parley.</head>
               <p>SWéeteſt Miſtreſſe <hi>F.</hi> aſſoone as it was my good happe to haue a ſight of ſome part of thoſe many graces and perfections, which euery able iudgement doth not only commend, but admire in you: I was not long in reſoluing with my ſelfe whether I ſhould ſerue and loue a creature ſo rare and worthie to be deſired. But I was longer in diſcourſing on the difference there is betwéene your worth and my little value, with the ſmall occaſion you haue to regard mée, conſidering I haue not béene yet ſo fortunate as to méet with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opportunitie that might furniſh mée with meanes to teſtifie vnto you how much I am truly deuoted to your ſeruice. Neither could I ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2723:70"/> ſoone reſolue whether I might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſcouer the hurt I receiued by the encounter of your beauties, and that affable patience which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day you were pleaſed to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate vnto my rude and tedious diſcourſe, whereas you deſerued the entertainment of a farre more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed ſpirit. Neuertheleſſe, relying on the greatneſſe and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of my affection, and the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your gentle diſpoſition, I haue not feared in all humilitie to make an offer of that command and power which in ſo ſhort a time you haue gotten ouer me, and which I very humbly beſéech you to accept of: ſo ſhall you haue a ſeruant, that in all things will yéeld you as much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as now with moſt zealous affection I kiſſe your faire and loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:70"/>
               <head>An earneſt proteſtation of perpetuall loue and loyaltie.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my euer honoured Miſtriſſe M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Iane H.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DEareſt Miſtriſſe, whenſoeuer you can enter into any doubt of my loialtie, thinke there is no truth remaining on the earth: for ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, you call euen certaintie it ſelfe into queſtion. I will alwaies bée more readie to conſent vnto the hate of my ſelfe, than to the loue of any other beautie, which I know muſt bée as farre inferiour to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of yours, as yours is aboue all others worthie and admirable. I beſeech you then to take this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of your ſlaue, that all the power hée can euer haue ouer his life and being, is altogether conſecrated
<pb facs="tcp:2723:71"/> to your ſeruice, and that heauen ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eſtabliſhed any thing more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than his inclination to honour you with all the fidelitie and affection you can poſſibly deſire: ſo that the worſt of abſence, fate, or miſfortune, ſhall ſerue but for better proofe and experience of it: to the which in all humilitie I leaue you, and my ſelfe to be nothing when I am not</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Wholly and only yours.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:71"/>
               <head>A ſad extaſie for the abſence of your Miſtriſſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To my truly-loued Miſtreſſe M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Mary S.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Did alwaies thinke (worthie Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe) that amorous paſſions had their effects more approching to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes than any other, and that whatſoeuer proceeded from them could not bée imagined by diſcourſe. The experience which now I ſo dearely make, fully aſſureth mée of it. I haue onely taſted the pleaſure one receiues from the ſight of a thing truly beloued, and thereby apprehend the perfection of content which the fruition yéelds. But I am at this inſtant ſo ſtrangely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with griefe for the priuation
<pb facs="tcp:2723:72"/> both of the one and the other, that hée that feeles it not, is not able to conceiue it, and hée that feeles it is not able to expreſſe it. I diſgeſt it then with as much patience, as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth neceſſitie, but yet excéedingly honoured in that I ſuffer for ſo rare and worthie a ſubiect, and liue, or rather entertaine the wearineſſe of my life, with ſo ſwéet a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and with the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo faire and <hi>Idea</hi> as yours. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alſo, that you chace not mine altogether from your eies, but let them ſée the image of your ſlaue ſo repleniſhed with fidelitie in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude, that it ſhall ſooner faile in Heauen than in him. And let not (I beſéech you) your faire vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſoule, which alwaies hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced actions elonged and cléere from the imperfections of other baſe and common ſpirits, be ſubiected to the ordinarie effects of time and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; but rather liue contented with affecting him that will die a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doring
<pb facs="tcp:2723:72"/> you: vnto whom, as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I haue, ſo will I euer be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The faithfulleſt of all Seruants.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Loue-letter, or the ſumme of Louers Rhetorike, in two figures, viz. <hi>Flatterie</hi> and <hi>Faining.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the moſt accompliſhed and rarely qualified Gentle-woman M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Iane H.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF either the excellencies of your beautie were leſſe, or they leſſe knowen to you than I know they
<pb facs="tcp:2723:73"/> are, I would not maruell (faireſt of all faire) if the preſumption of theſe lines ſhould giue you cauſe of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. But where there is ſuch an admirable concurrence of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as in your moſt accompliſhed ſelfe; I hold it impoſſible for any compoſition of mortalitie to be proofe againſt them: from whence I may well deriue an aſſurance, that you cannot thinke it ſtrange, if I ſay, (as indeede I truly may) that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any oppoſition which by the ableſt ſeconding of reaſon I could make, I finde my ſelfe but fleſh and bloud, too weake a temper to withſtand the vnreſiſtable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of your preuailing eies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing I may well terme them, that in a moment haue not onely depriued me of my libertie, leauing mee nothing frée ſaue the zeale of an vnfained deuotion to your ſeruice; but reduced my will, and euerie power of my ſoule vnder the ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch Lawes as ſhall pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:2723:73"/> either your rigour or mercie to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine. Séeing then I can haue no other being but that which would be farre more wretched than wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe it ſelfe, vnleſſe you pleaſe to bleſſe it with the happineſſe of your fauour, then let not the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of it (I beſéech you) be the cauſe of his death, that cannot, nay that will not liue without it, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſuch compaſſion and regard on my ſufferings, as the gracious ſwéetneſſe of your innated goodneſſe doth promiſe, and as is due to the infiniteneſſe of my affection: which for faith and loyaltie ſhall alwaies bee incompatible of all compariſon, and for conſtancie ſo vnmatched, that neither time nor fortune, which vnto all things vnder Heauen bring alteration and end, ſhall euer bée of power to ſhake it with the leaſt motion of change, or determine it ſooner than the lateſt inſtant of my breath. And this I vow with as much reſolution, as I humbly pray
<pb facs="tcp:2723:74"/> you would vouchſafe to let mée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how you pleaſe to diſpoſe of your creature, who together with his life and fortunes is and eternally will be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The very ſlaue of your commandements.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:74"/>
               <head>Another of like Argument.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the faire, but farre more vnkind Gentle-woman, Miſtriſſe Elizabeth C.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HAd I any power left mée (cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Beautie) ouer my deſires, I could bée contented to diſcourſe alone with my ſelfe on the paſſion of my too wretched condition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out importuning ſo obdurate an hart as yours, that vnwilling to frée mée, taketh pleaſure to entertaine mée in it: but ſince loue hath wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them vnder his lawes, and the ſubiection of your commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; pardon mée I beſéech you, if conſtrained by them, I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to your pitie, as the onely meane I can hope for of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the torment of my pains.
<pb facs="tcp:2723:75"/> And were it not proper to the ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your diſpoſition, yet you owe it vnto him that honoureth you more than all the world, that ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you as the onely marke of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie which hée acknowledgeth héere below, that hath no life but by you, that deſireth it not but for you, and to be ſo happie as to ſpend it in your ſeruice: whereunto I am ſo deuoted, that truth ſhall ſooner faile in the ordinances of Heauen, than in this reſolution of mine. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this my deuotion then, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it by what Lawes you pleaſe, draw out of it all the proofes which either my life or death are able to giue you. And let not crueltie, that hath ſome limit euen in thoſe to whom it is naturall, bée the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtaine of your faire vertues, nor permit mée to finde more grace in death than in you; who grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with my miſeries, may rather end them by the end of my life, than you by the grant of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
<pb facs="tcp:2723:75"/> which onely is of power to make mee the happieſt, as without it I am now</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The moſt vnhappieſt of men.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another not vnlike.</head>
               <p>OF all other moſt cruell Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, to my infinite griefe I finde, that no greater happineſſe can arriue vnto wretched louers, than to meet with death whenſoeuer they call for it. Upon the writing of my laſt vnto you, I did not thinke the Bearer at his returne ſhould haue found mée aliue. And yet, alas! I liue ſtill, but ſtrangely grieued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot die, and that there is no hope of remedie for mee in any
<pb facs="tcp:2723:76"/> but in you, who it ſéemes taketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to entertaine mée in torments. My teares wherewithall you ſée this paper all beblubbered, and my paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons together, will not ſuffer mee to ſay any more, but onely once for all to put my ſelfe vpon your mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, from the which if ſpéedily I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not comfort, euer after it will come too late. And this I proteſt as farre from diſſimulation as I am néere vnto mine end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:76"/>
               <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the ſweet and vertuous Gentle-woman M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>GEntle Miſtris <hi>I.</hi> If I did think the enemity of our parents had as much intereſt in your thoughts, as loue hath in mine, I would rather dye to giue you ſatiſfaction, then liue to be hated of a gentle woman whom I affect and honour more then all the world. But aſſuring my ſelfe that ſo ſwéete and accompliſhed a beauty as yours, cannot bee accompanied with any ſuch vnfriendly diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to wiſh ill vnto him, that farre beyond all reach of apprehenſion is vnfainedly deuoted to your ſeruice, I preſume to entreate you to haue ſo much regard to your owne goodnes and the compaſſion of my endurings, as to grant mee the fauour of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, that ſo I may haue opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:2723:77"/> to acquaint you: more at large with that, which I hope wil redound to your contentment, and my infinite good. And this mee thinks I ſhould promiſe my ſelfe out of that more than ordinary reſpect and good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance which of late it hath pleaſed you to ſhew me, at leaſt wiſe, if flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering my ſelfe, I do not wrongfully apply that to my particular aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, which is indifferently conferred on others by the curteſie of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious nature. Howſoeuer in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion I attend your reſolution héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: and no leſſe hartily beſéeching the Almighty to continue you in his grace, than I deſire to liue and dye in yours, I commit you to this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that I am no longer mine own but</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Altogether at your diſpoſing.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:77"/>
               <head>Another, no leſſe earneſt, though perhaps leſſe honeſt.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To the excellent in all beauty, beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Miſtris Francis R.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SO long as I was able by any ſtrength of reaſon or other ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whatſoeuer (fayreſt miſtreſſe <hi>R.)</hi> to make head againſt the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of thoſe paſſions, which for a long time together haue very ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicted me, I neuer offered more than by lookes, to diſcouer them vnto you, who only are the cauſe of them, and onely can giue them remedy. But now that I finde my ableſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be but a weake and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſiſtance againſt the fury of my ſufferings, which continually aſſault mee with ſuch apprehenſions of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that all the paynes in the
<pb facs="tcp:2723:78"/> world put together, and compared with them are but light and tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pardon mee, I humbly pray, if caſting my ſelfe at the féete of your mercy, I preſume with all the vows of my ſoule to employ ſuch commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of my caſe, as the preſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of it requires. If you looke vnto my deſerts, I know them to bée moſt vnworthy of the leaſt regard. It is not vpon them I muſt ſtand (for indéede what merit can ſtand before the eminence of your worth) but if you deigne to deſcend ſo low as the conſideration of your ſeruant, looke I beſéech you with a pittifull and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding eye vnto the integrity of my faith, the reſolution of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, the trueth of my affection, and the vnbounded zeale I leaue to the obedience of your commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe are they whereupon I build the hopes of your fauour, and that is it alone whereunto all my wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes runne, there is nothing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired I ſo much deſire; in regard of it
<pb facs="tcp:2723:78"/> the whole empire of the world ſhould be of a very vile and contemptible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect with me. Upon whom then can you better or more worthily conferre it, then on him that holds it in ſo high an eſtimation, and that by all the duties of an humble, loyall, and truly deuoted ſeruice will before all others whatſoeuer euer ſéeke to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue you for his ſwéeteſt and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſtreſſe, as I hope and infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray you would bee pleaſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto me in your returne héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Upon the expectation whereof I haue vtterly diſclaimed all other being, to be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Wholly your creature.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:2723:79"/>
               <head>A ſeemely anſwer to ſuch a Suitor.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>To Maſter H.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SIr, if I carried as little reſpect to my huſbands good, as it appeares you haue care of your owne ſafety, I might quickly take a courſe would prooue as preiudiciall to you, as the lewdneſſe of your preſumption de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues. You very much miſtake me if you take me to be any of thoſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it ſéems you make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practiſe of ſuch addreſſes, for by the grace of God I wil alwaies beany thing ſooner, than a ſubiect fitting for one of your filthy diſpoſition. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell what ſhould moue you to aſſaile me in this ſort? hath my behauiour béene ſo light (for ſure I am I neuer exchanged word with you in my life) or my lookes ſo wanton to incourage you vnto it? No, I defie you, and all
<pb facs="tcp:2723:79"/> the world in that regard, and I think if I ſhould put it vpon your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you muſt ſay my carriage hath euer béen ſuch, as would rather mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie then ſtirrs vp ſuch wicked and vnlawfull affections. But what do I meane to conteſt thus with a man, that hath no other ends or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then the ſatiſfaction of his bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh deſires, and to that purpoſe would ſet vpon euen modeſty and chaſtifie themſelues were they to be ſéene vnder the forme of women. In a word then, ſince you perceius my inclination to be as farre from yours, as yours is from all vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I would wiſh you, if you loue your life, to deſiſt from moleſting mée any more in this kinde: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be you well aſſured I will make you féele how dangerous it is to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the honour of ſuch, as hold it in a farre more eſtéeme than their deareſt liues.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
